<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vickers challenge claiming a maintainance as due by proofes out of the gospell : wherein is manifested, that there is a competencie due unto them / by Ios. Meene, vicker.</title>
            <author>Meene, Joshua.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07397</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17780.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2818</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24759815</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24759815</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27872</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07397)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27872)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1856:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vickers challenge claiming a maintainance as due by proofes out of the gospell : wherein is manifested, that there is a competencie due unto them / by Ios. Meene, vicker.</title>
                  <author>Meene, Joshua.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 74 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Nicholas Vavasour, at his shop in the Inner-Temple neere the church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another issue with cancelled t.p. of: A liberall maintenance is manifestly due to the ministers of the gospell.--Cf. STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴ B-K⁴ L² (last leaf wanting or blank?).</note>
                  <note>Pages 63-64 (signature I4) bound out of order between pages 60 and 61.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Salaries, etc.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27872:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27872:1"/>
            <p>THE VICKERS CHAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LENGE. CLAIMING A MAINTAINANCE AS DVE BY PROOFES OVT OF THE GOSPELL.</p>
            <p>Wherein is manifeſted, that there is a Competencie due un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</p>
            <p>By IOS: MEENE, <hi>Vicker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed, And are to be ſold by <hi>Nicholas Vavaſour,</hi> at his ſhop in the Inner-Temple neere the Church. 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27872:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27872:2"/>
            <head>Deo Optimo Maximo Patri, Filio, Spiritui Sancto, Deo Trino &amp; uni;</head>
            <head type="sub">Cui Eccleſia cognita &amp; chara, tanquam oculi pupilla: &amp; à quo ejus Miniſtri duplici honore digni habentur; Sacrilegii autem Iudici juſtiſſimo, vindici infenſiſſimo:</head>
            <p>Minuta duo cum vidua illa paupercula in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelio; ſeu potius minutum unum piae volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatis caetera omnia minuta compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendens idem etiam ipſum hoc ſequenti opuſculo complexum, in gazophylacium divinum humillimè mittit humillimus, minimus in Divinis Miniſter.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joſhua Meen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:27872:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27872:3"/>
            <head>To the judicious and indifferent <hi>Reader, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">A Preface apologeticall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are ſundry learned and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Treatiſes extant in the behalf of the Clergie for their competent maintenance, and touching their right unto the tithes.</p>
            <p>To omit the Ancients and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigue Authours, obſerve how no few of our owne Nation have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in this neceſſary and pious ſubject: as the right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Fathers in God, the Lord Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> the Lord Biſhop <hi>Carlton,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>Henry Spilman,</hi> Sir <hi>Iames Sempell,</hi> Doctor <hi>Tilleſſie,</hi> Doctor <hi>Mayer,</hi> Doctor <hi>Rives,</hi> Maſter <hi>Hooker,</hi> Maſter <hi>Roberts:</hi> from ſome of whoſe Works in this kinde, I do freely acknowledge my ſelf to have received no ſmall furtherance.</p>
            <p>There are likewiſe other famous Writers beſides, which although altogether unknowne to mee, ſhall nevertheleſſe with theſe ſpoken of, be immortalized by their devout and ſolid lines to this purpoſe. Although alas too true it is, that through the deep-rooted corruption of this deplorate ſeaſon, their excellent endevours this way have not attained a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed event. Wherupon ſome may cenſure my pains herein at this preſent, as audacious and fruitleſſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:27872:4"/>
            <p>Yet I conceive it cannot be amiſſe to continue diſcourſe in a caſe of that conſequence: neither is it reaſon to leave our juſt claime, whiles we wrongfully loſe our true right.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the bringing of the matter into frequent mention (though in a weaker manner) may prove a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull means to make thoſe godly and judicious Authours to be better read over and againe revolved, whoſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments well conſidered will appear ſufficient to confound the adverſary, and to end the controverſie. It may alſo put men of the beſt ability in mindeto manage the buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>Further the manifold dangers of execrable facriledge ought to ſtirre up every competent perſon to deviſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all poſſible remedies againſt her perillous oversprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>Surely the prophane ſuppoſall that it was never divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appointed for the Miniſters of the Gospell to be mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with tithes, &amp;c. But to live as it were, upon ſtipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darie Almes, is an errour inweeded in the minds of no few folks of more then ordinary wealth and place.</p>
            <p>And the accurſed contagion thereof doth daily diffuſe it ſelfe farre and neer, yea, and that not ſeldome, into worſer degrees.</p>
            <p>Inſomuch that now no few feare not nor bluſh to finde fault with the payment of the tenths, not onely nuder ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill of an obliterate and cancelled Judiciall currant amongſt the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> but alſo under diſcredit of a Leviticall and unlawfull Ceremonie, diſanulled at the comming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This grievous miſchief in theſe perverſe times ſeemes grown to that great height, that now any parcell of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the right of the Church, though never ſo properly deduced from the text, and never ſo piouſly intended, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth for the moſt part, a common hatred and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſcandall of a covetous and trouble ſome man.</p>
            <p>I could exemplifie thus much without travelling farre from my own Pariſh, and with no little ſorrow ſhew at large
<pb facs="tcp:27872:4"/>what a world of unconſcionable cuſtomes, and compoſitions are moſt obſtinately, and overpowringly maint ained againſt the Church, by fockes of eminent wealth, and credit, beſides the ordinary rankes.</p>
            <p>Moreover I might mention, that no leſſe ridiculous then injurious wreſting of the Statute of caſe of tithe wood, that the Mother freeth the Daughter, namely if the body bee above twenty yeares old, then the top, although put to firing muſt be freed from tithing; which moſt unjuſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity findoth, notwithſtanding no few Patrones, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſome of the Law-profeſſours, to the extreme preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>I might yet remember ſome worſer matter, namely glebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands detained by ſundry perſons of no ſmall wealth and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme in this world, from the Church, appearing neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe upon record, Terriers, and other ſufficient teſtimonies, ploinely to belong thereunto.</p>
            <p>Surely when as I ſeriouſly conſider the worldly wiſedome, wealth and place relucent in ſome of thoſe that deale thus unjuſtly with the Church: Behold the charitobleſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, which I can make of their actions, is to feare they are unfortiuately lapſed into the foreſaid errour againſt ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, &amp;c. And ſo whiles they pretand onely to allow us ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, they unconſcionably leave us to all extremities.</p>
            <p>Finally, the publiſhing of this Treatiſe proceedeth not forth without the private incouragements of ſome of my learned brethren of the Clergie.</p>
            <p>To conclude, the moſt gracious God ſeemeth in theſe dayes to have in a ſpecialler manner compaſſionately looked upon the calamitous eſtate of his oppreſſed Church, by ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us a Prince very propitiouſly inclined for her good: He hath alſo vouchſafed us many pious Prelats; noble and honorable perſonages, Judges, Lawyers, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eaymen of no little worth, devoutly tendring in their proper ranks, therelief and right of the Church.</p>
            <p>Neither is the paternall good will of my religiouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Dioceſan to ſuccour my diſtreſſed Vicaridge a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:27872:5"/>of ſmall moment to animate. Moreover the courteous favour of that learned &amp; vertuous Knight Sir <hi>Nathanael Brent</hi> in this kinde to my ſelfe in particular, beſides others. I may juſtly adde the good Offices done me this way, by our Right Worſhipfull Archdeacons in this Dioceſſe, Doctor <hi>Binge</hi> and Maſter <hi>White:</hi> Alſo the free and honeſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in this caſe of Doctor <hi>Talbot,</hi> indeared unto the Clergy by his affection, and fidelity towards them.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, the promiſed aſſiſtance of my very worthy friend and wonted refuge, in many malevolent and Sacrilegious projects, and practiſes againſt me in my Pariſh, namely the Right Worſhipfull Maſter <hi>Thomas Talbot</hi> Eſquire, &amp;c. the glory of the place were he liveth.</p>
            <p>The generall condolement and clamour, through the whole Countrey, of all well affected children of the Church. (which know this miſerable Vicaridge) at the extreme diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion betweene the great burden of the Cure, and the poore pittance of the meanes to ſuſtaine it with.</p>
            <p>Surely, none of theſe premiſſes but have ſome force and weight: And therefore all of them conſidered together, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but prove very ponderous to induce, and perſwade mee for Sions ſake not to hold my peace, and remaine ſilent: But rather (in the willingly acknowledged weakeneſſe and ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of my abilities) to imploy my beſt endeavours, as a dutifull Son, in the humble ſervice of our holy and venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Mother the Church.</p>
            <p>And in all reverence and lowlineſſe of mind, I cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſubmit them unto the Cenſure of my Eccleſiaſticall Superiours.</p>
            <p>Farewell in the Authour of all welfare, Chriſt Ieſus; to whom, with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, three perſons and one God, be all honour and glory for evermore. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy Servant in the Lord,</hi> Ioſhua Meene.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27872:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 9 chap. part of the 9 verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out the corne.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Oxe knoweth his owner (the Prophet <hi>Jſaiah</hi> expreſſeth) I might thus invert the words in a myſticall ſenſe; Many an ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner knoweth not his Oxe. For if he did take meet notice of him as he ought, it would be a means to make him change the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his cruell muzzles, into competent maintenance.</p>
            <p>But as a righteous man regardeth the life, of his beaſt, ſo the bowels of the wicked are cruell, <hi>Salomon</hi> ſheweth. Theſe times of Church-robberie might in ſome ſort be ſaid to reſemble the ſeaſon of <hi>Iobs</hi> calamitie; <hi>The Oxen were plowing, and the Aſſes feeding beſides them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It falleth out in theſe dayes of ours quite contrary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the diſcourſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41. of King <hi>Pharaohs</hi> dreame: for behold the fat Oxen, the high fleſhed Bulles of <hi>Baſhan</hi> doe eate up the leane ones by devouring their due means. How ſhould they then be ſtrong to labour, that there be no breaking in nor going out, no complaining in our ſtreets, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.</p>
            <p>Let us pray the Lord of the great harveſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. that he would ſend forth labourers into his field, and into his Barne, and that they may be liberally allowed whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27872:6"/>is requiſite for their painfull places. And that through his grace, the men of this world may be drawne and moved to practiſe this divine precept: <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the corne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Apoſtle here appeareth like that excellent hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſholder in the Goſpell, which bringeth forth out of his treaſury things new and old: for when as he had alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, what liberty hee might have juſtly aſſumed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in ſundry other particulars; loe he proceedeth to a further inſtance touching that freedome hee could alſo rightly take, by vertue of his miniſteriall function, in the matter of maintenance.</p>
            <p>To warrant the goodneſſe of this his claime and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, he ſeemeth to fetch ayd and ſupport out of the old Teſtament. For confirmation of this point, to raiſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe fit ſupplyes of freſh forces to the ſame purpoſe out of the new.</p>
            <p>The ſenſe of the words, and the ſeverall parts of this Text ſhall receive their diſpatch together.</p>
            <p>Obſerve then firſt the commander, ſecondly, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon commanded: thirdly, the command it ſelfe: fourthly, the reaſon of the command.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Touching the Commander. If wee conſider him as he is ſupreme; behold he is the eternall Law-giver. But if we regard him as he is ſubordinate, then we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſervant.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Touching the perſon commanded in the word <hi>thou,</hi> let us comprehend in this circumſtance, primari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the children of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> ſecondarily, all people.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Touching the command it ſelfe in this clauſe, <hi>ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe. Aquinas</hi> admoniſheth to underſtand this ſentence: firſt literally of Oxen, which <hi>Ainſworth</hi> affirmeth, are here named but for an inſtance, all other ſorts of labouring and uſefull beaſts being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe meant under that terme: ſecondly, ſpiritually, of the Miniſters of the world, the may in no ſort be muzzled.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27872:6"/>Or at the Chaldee Paraphraſt rendreth it, have their mouthes tyed up with the cruell cords of ſacriledge.</p>
            <p>The ſenſe for the Oxen is plaine as the words ſound, (ſaith <hi>Abulenſis</hi>) but yet it is not the principall; for the ſenſe which concerneth the Miniſters is chiefe, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially intended of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Touching the reaſon of the command thus rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>that treadeth out the corne;</hi> or as others reade it, <hi>when he treadeth, in his treading or threſhing:</hi> In thoſe dayes flayles were not in uſe, but the feet of beaſts, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10. other whiles wheeles, ſometime ſtones, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.</p>
            <p>One of the Hebrew Rabbines recordeth a law currant in that nation, with a penalty upon the offending perſon; How the beaſt muſt not be hindred from feeding in his plowing, ſowing, reaping the crop, treading out the corne, carriage of burdens, &amp;c. All which (Expoſitours write) muſt be myſtically reflected upon the Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Prieſts. <hi>Thou ſhall not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The doctrine from the premiſſes may be collected in this forme: <hi>The Miniſters of the Goſpell which labour in getting out and exhibiting the graine of Gods word unto the people, muſt in no wiſe be debarred from the meanes of their meet maintenance in that reſpect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For proofe of this point: firſt, we will muſter up toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the arguments of our Apoſtle in this preſent chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: ſecondly, wee will adjoyne ſome collaterall places for confirmation of the premiſſes: thirdly, wee will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the certainty of our propoſition from the nature and exigencie of the place of the Miniſtery: fourthly, we will declare the truth of this doctrine from the dueneſſe of tythes by divine right to the Miniſters of the Goſpell: fiftly, wee will prove the poynt by diſcourſe of the une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall condition of Impropriations: ſixtly, wee will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate our obſervation from the recitall of ſundry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences, which are incurred through defect of its due execution.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:27872:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A threefold cord is not quickly broken,</hi> was part of King <hi>Salomons</hi> Sermon. <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 4. the ſame ſtrength in perſwaſion befalls this ſixefold combination. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Wee will muſter up together the arguments of our Apoſtle in this preſent chapter: wherein wee might not amiſſe profeſſe, how hee unclaſpeth a double volume touching the caſe; namely, the booke of nature, and the booke of Gods word.</p>
            <p>In the booke of nature, firſt we may behold him argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the matter with an aſſembly of ſimilitudes gathered together from the vocations of warre and peace, verſe 7. <hi>Who goeth a warfare at any time at his owne charges? who planteth a vineyard, and eateth not of the fruit thereof? or who feedeth a flocke, and eateth not of the milke of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As then ſouldiers have deſervedly their due ſtipends: as husbandmen reape their anſwerable fruits: as ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards receive their paſtorall profits: Surely ſo muſt the ſpirituall Miniſters, the chariots and horſemen of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Captaines of Chriſtian companies under the great Generall our Lord Ieſus, have their full pay and wages. So muſt the myſticall husbandmen in the Vineyard and Garden of his Church, freely participate of the grapes and fruits of their paines and plantations. So muſt the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards of mens ſoules receive meet benefit from among their tended flockes, and be fed with the milke of nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing fathers and nurcing mothers breaſts.</p>
            <p>As the Souldier meriteth his military ſtipend, the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard-planter his wine, the Shepheard his wooll: So muſt the ſpirituall Paſtors (repreſenting all theſe callings in a divers kinde) be thought to deſerve, and indeed receive liberall recompence for their labours.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Herein we might ſee our Apoſtle making his matter good from the manner of other Teachers: their example he aſſumeth as ſufficient evidence for himſelfe. Since their practiſe was to take of the people meanes for their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27872:7"/>and it was a lawfull courſe for them ſo to doe; The conſequence then ſeemed very good and juſtifiable for him to uſe no leſſe liberty.</p>
            <p>Yea being a chiefe Apoſtle, a principall Teacher, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to have ſo much the more licence herein the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ordinary Miniſters. Thus verſe 12. <hi>If others be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of this power over you, are not we rather?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dux milite major, ratem qui temperat, anteit remigis officium:</hi> If the common Souldier may juſtly challenge a competent part of the ſpoyle, then may the Generall well expect a richer portion, a prey of divers colours of needle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, <hi>Iudges</hi> 5. And if the Marriner can rightly claime any priviledge, then can the Pilot lawfully demand mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of more preheminence.</p>
            <p>So where a ſimple Prieſt hath a ſufficient intereſt, much more an Apoſtle, a Prelate hath a title in a higher degree prevalent.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In the booke of Gods word, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth aſſure this matter with an invincible power of divine decrees. <hi>Say J theſe things as a man</hi> (he expoſtulateth) <hi>or ſaith not the law the ſame alſo?</hi> for it is written, he ſheweth, in the law of <hi>Moſes, Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the corne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth God take care for Oxen? or ſaith he it altogether for our ſakes? no doubt this is, that hee that ploweth ſhould plow in hope, and hee that threſheth in hope, ſhould be partaker of his hope, <hi>verſes.</hi> 8.9.10.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle here appeareth with a Prolepſis in his ſpeeches; for he preventeth that objection, which ſome might perchance oppoſe againſt theſe ſimilitudes aſſumed from worldly things, becauſe of the difference of humane matters from divine: wherefore hee confirmeth the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate of naturall reaſon with the determination of the law of the Lord, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>The argument is drawne in this place, firſt, from the leſſer to the greater: if Gods providence be thus good
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27872:8"/>and gracious toward Oxen, ſurely then it ſhineth in a more excellent manner of care for the children of men.</p>
            <p>His ſtatute touching Oxen, Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> telleth us, was not intended there to ſtay, and to ſtretch no further; but it meant more eſpecially humane creatures, moſt of all the Miniſters of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>When as then the eyes of all living wights wait upon the Lord, and he giveth them their meat in due ſeaſon, he openeth his hand and ſarisfieth the deſire of every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: he giveth to the beaſt his food, and to the young Ravens that cry, hee cauſeth the graſſe to grow for the cattell, he ſendeth the Springs into the vallies to give them drinke, and that the wilde Aſſes may quench their thirſt. Hee appointeth the fowles of the heaven their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, which ſing among the branches, the Cedars to make their neſts, and for the Storke an houſe of firre trees: the high hils a refuge for the wilde Goats, and the rockes for the Conies, as we reade in the Pſalmiſt. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Sparrowes, (two of which are ſold for a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing) be under his protection, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. yea, hee hath vouchſafed to make a ſolemne law and conſtitution in the behalfe of oxen for their allowance.</p>
            <p>Certainly then his pleaſure is plaine, his precept is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, that the ſpirituall oxen of the Clergie, which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the field of his Church, muſt never bee muzzled from enjoying the juſt meanes of their painefull places.</p>
            <p>If under the example of the Oxe (as <hi>Rabbi Solomon</hi> inferreth) a due proviſion of ſuſtence for every labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring beaſt is enacted, and no unequall dealing touching them diſpenſed with.</p>
            <p>Behold then the Eccleſiaſticall toylers muſt doe it in hope, and follow their worke with fruition of reward: yea indeed ruling well, and being diligent in word and doctrine, be counted worthy of double honour, for the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the Oxe that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out the corn, and the labourer is worthy of his reward,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:27872:8"/>
            <p>Thus the bruit beaſts (as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> alſo conceive) which at firſt were made for the uſe of men, are like wiſe here mentioned not ſo much for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as moſt for their ſakes. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Our Apoſtle evinceth his aſſertion by undenyable termes of compariſon, or he draweth an argument from the greater to the leſſe: <hi>Jf we have ſowne unto you ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things, is it a great thing if wee ſhall reape your carnall things,</hi> verſe 11. As if he ſhould have ſaid, if we provide for your ſoules, it is a poore recompence that you ſhould provide for our bodies, becauſe as the ſoule farre way excelleth the body, ſo the food for the ſoule very much ſurmounteth the price and worth of bodily ſood.</p>
            <p>If we of the Miniſtery bring you bagges which waxe not old, a treaſure in the heavens that faileth not, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as neither thieſe approacheth, nor moath corrupteth, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. Then open your earthly purſes, grudge not your tranſitory treaſures in that manner which Almighty God hath commanded for our maintenance.</p>
            <p>If we bring you <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. that one pearle of great price; that invaluable treaſure hid in a field; loſe it not then by ſparing of coſt, caſt it not away for feare of charge, but imitate that devout and wiſe Merchant man there commended, who forſooke and ſold any worldly thing he had, for to buy that field, to purchaſe that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pearle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quae vos nobis rependitis nequaquam collatis in vos be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiis reſpondent: nos aterna, ſpiritualiae, coeleſtia offeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; vos fluxa, temporalia, caduca, fragilia refertis.</hi> Alas would men make an impartiall eſtimate in this matter, they would ſoone then conclude with themſelves, that there is no proportionable compariſon between thoſe good things they bring to their Paſtors, and thoſe glad tidings brought by their Miniſters unto them, betweene the bread of the earth, and the bread of heaven, between the meat which periſheth, &amp; the meat which indureth.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:27872:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Quis ignorat ſpiritualia carnalibus eſſe multo praeſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiora?</hi> what is the temporall tythe which Pariſhioners returne their Prieſts, if wee conſider the eternall truth which the Prieſts teach their Pariſhioners? what, ſeemes the ſheaves of corne to ſtand in any termes of worth with their ſentences of comfort? how vile appeare their payments to the vertue of their prayers? how poore are their offerings to the price of their orations? <hi>O fortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos nimium, bona ſiſua norint, agricolas!</hi> Oh happy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey men if they knew their owne advantage in this change; if they would well count what huge and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oddes of gain they get by reaſon of this permutation!</p>
            <p>Let me expoſtulate a little with them to inform them aright. Is the expence of corruptible Mammon equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to the purchaſe of coeleſtiall Sermons? Is the gift of glebes of anſwerable value to the gain of godlineſſe? are <hi>Lammas</hi> profits of like excellency as the fruits of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe?</p>
            <p>Can the contents of this preſent wilderneſſe counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile the commodities of the land of promiſe? doth droſſe equall gold? will water match wines? may earth mate heaven? can vanity compare with eternity?</p>
            <p>Surely, I would wiſh thoſe worldly minded perſons, which preſume upon ſuch diſproportionable paradoxes, to annoint their eyes with eye-ſalve, that they may ſee, <hi>Apocalypſe</hi> 3. Then they will not onely ſoone diſcerne an infinite diſtance betweene the vertue and worth of theſe ſeverals, but moreover certainly determine touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this point, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. If they have been made partakers of their ſpirituall things, their duty alſo is to miniſter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them in carnall things, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Our Apoſtle fortifieth his caſe with an argument from Gods ordinance in this wiſe; <hi>Doe not ye know that they which miniſter about holy things, live of the things of the Temple? and they which wait at the Altar, are partakers
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27872:9"/>with the Altar?</hi> even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpell, ſhould live of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, verſes 13.14.</p>
            <p>What God the Father primarily conſtituted in this caſe, was not afterwards cancelled by God the Sonne, ſaith <hi>Aretius,</hi> for there is the ſame reaſon alwayes ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of conſerving the worſhip of God. And that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was amongſt all nations (he noteth) by a publique maintenance. This publique worke requireth publique wages, <hi>Aquinas</hi> writeth.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſome have here ſuppoſed, how the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this place hath a twofold reflection, namely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Prieſts of the Lord, and the Prieſts of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. <hi>Ipſa naturalis ratio hoc habet, ut quis inde vivat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de laborat:</hi> Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> affirmeth, how even naturall reaſon alledgeth thus much, that folkes muſt look to live of that function, wherein they labour.</p>
            <p>By a divine law in the old Teſtament, the Miniſters had a publique and certaine proviſion of meanes ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for their liberall maintenance, therefore much more the Miniſters of the new Teſtament, becauſe their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery is the moſt excellent.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts of the Heathens had likewiſe this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; good reaſon then that the Prieſts of the Chriſtians ſhould receive herein no leſſe, but rather a large allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>If any would plead, why pretend you the Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> unto us, who are not now obliged to theſe antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted rules living under the Goſpell?</p>
            <p>Behold Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in this place oppoſeth againſt them the divine appointment afreſh: But if they replyed, when did that appeare? we anſwer, even in that ſeaſon, when our Saviour Chriſt ſent forth his Diſciples, inhibiting them to make proviſion for their owne ſelves, as moſt due unto them from others in regard for their labour and paines: threatning alſo ſuch as welcomed them not in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27872:10"/>this contribution beſides attention.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calvin</hi> here collected how the Miniſters, ſhould not live on thoſe whom they teach, as depending upon almes (according to the errour of the Anabaptiſts) but upon the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>For the Lord ſaith <hi>Theophylact,</hi> hath ſo determined the matter, by enacting in the new Teſtament. Lawes conformable to the old. So that after what manner hee had anciently ſet downe, that he who ſerveth about the Altar, muſt live of the Altar.</p>
            <p>So now hee likewiſe ſheweth, how the Evangelicall Preachers, muſt not live barely of the peoples allowance, but of the Goſpell, leaſt perchance their auditours would wax proud and domineering over them, through aſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling conceit, that they had their meanes from them, and ſo were beholding unto them.</p>
            <p>The maintenance then of the Miniſtery (it is here ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt) ought not to bee eleemoſynarie, or upon bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence: but a ſetled and affixed portion: namelie the tith of the increaſe of the fruites of the earth.</p>
            <p>For theſe ſeeme fitteſt by Gods owne ordinance of them; firſt, to the Leviticall Prieſthood, and ſecondly, after the change of that Service, by way of intailement of them to the Miniſters of the Goſpell. Whereby (Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> declareth) the Prieſts which by right receive them, may not be upbraded; and the Pariſhioners, who are bound to pay them, muſt not boaſt nor bee puffed up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth &amp;c.</hi> wee are now ſecondly, to adjoyne ſome collaterall places for confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the premiſſes. I will not bee tedious with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, the tender of this one place unto you, <hi>Galatians</hi> the 6. may ſeeme ſufficient: <hi>Let him that is taught in the Word, communicate unto him that teacheth in all good things. Be not deceived: God is not mocked: for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever a man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reape, &amp;c.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:27872:10"/>in this paſſage appeareth to uſe very ſignificant ſpeeches for the purpoſe. It is not amiſſe to examine them in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious manner, that we may the more evidently perceive, what a neceſſary duty lyeth upon the Laity to render backe a good returne of temporals unto the Miniſters of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>The firſt word which hee uſeth is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, let him communicate; by this terme Saint <hi>Chryoſtome</hi> tels us how he intimateth that there muſt bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and intercourſe, a flux and reflux of heavenly and earthly things, betweene the Prieſt &amp; the Pariſh. Iuſtice it ſelfe challengeth thus much, for men to expreſſe their due thankfulneſſe toward their Teachers, by bountifull recompencing of their Paſtorall labours with abundant ſupplies of all conveniences.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hee uſeth the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which terme may be taken for the delivering of any doctrine, by the organ of the voyce to inſtruct others in the myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion. The Apoſtle therefore in this place, appeareth to put a plaine difference betweene the labouring and lazie Miniſters, betweene the diligent Bees and idle Drones, between the induſtrious treaders out of the corne, and the voluptuous caters up of the corne.</p>
            <p>There muſt bee <hi>ratio dati et accepti,</hi> ſaith <hi>Arboreus,</hi> a true reckoning on both ſides; the Paſtour muſt piouſly imploy his talent, and the Pariſhioner muſt profitably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in his element; the Miniſter muſt performe his part, and the Auditour muſt doe his duty: the Sower muſt reape, and the receiver muſt returne a croppe with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, we meete with the manner of communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſubjoyned, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in all good things: not in a few, but in all; love, reverence, and maintenance, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius</hi> noteth, expreſſing al liberalitie towards them, Saint <hi>Chryoſtome</hi> obſerveth. Which they may very well
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27872:11"/>fulfill (theſe Fathers affirme) as receiving much more, then they can returne.</p>
            <p>This is a rule ſaith Doctor <hi>Mayer</hi> to ſupply the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with all neceſſaries; eſpecially (as is moſt agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the divine Law) the people are hereby injoyned freely and willingly to communicate in all thoſe goods, which bee the ſeverall increaſes of their fruites of the earth unto them.</p>
            <p>Surely this verſe ſeemeth very powerfull againſt no ſmall number of covetous worldlings. Some will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part nothing at all to their Paſtours maintenance, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perforce: ſome will expend in this caſe but a poore and unworthy pittance. Some beſides wretched miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableneſſe uſe wicked deceit &amp; fraud in their payments. They pretend ill trading, how their corne is thinne, their cattle did not thrive, their fruits were few, &amp;c. the times are hard, their charge is great, their meanes be ſmall, &amp;c. But this I ſay, <hi>hee that ſoweth ſparingly ſhall reape ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and hee which ſoweth bounlifully ſhall reape bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> 2 <hi>Corinthians</hi> 3. Theſe covetous Idolaters carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves cleane contrary to the Apoſtles precept: behold hee pleadeth for liberality, but they practiſe parſimony; he is for ſincerity, but they for ſubtilty; he deſireth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dealing, but they delight in impoſtures.</p>
            <p>Let not then men thus impiouſly erre in this enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed communicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their goods. It is beſt for every one to take heede of deceitfull excuſes in this kind, <hi>Anſelmus</hi> admoniſheth; becauſe although humane creatures may be often deluded, yet the alſeeing Lord, the ſearcher of the heart and the reynes is never gone beyond. Theſe cunning pretexts may coozen many men, but the Lord doth eaſily diſcerne through the cloſeſt miſt of thei Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious falſhood, Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſheweth.</p>
            <p>This ſinne is much greater then you ſuppoſe, ſaith <hi>Aretius,</hi> God is not mocked, there will follow a doomeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day booke, a reckoning ſeaſon, when as ſuch baſe mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27872:11"/>Earthwormes ſhall reape as they have ſowne; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for their corrupt and unconſcionable dealing, the proper wages thereof, that is to ſay, eternal death and damnation.</p>
            <p>Theſe Church-robbing ſinnes, which now not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome miniſter matter of laughter to profane worldlings, and ſeeme but veniall in their ſeduced imaginations, will then ſhew forth a ſcarlet colour, a crimſon dy of a mournefull and mortall nature amongſt the greateſt and moſt grievous offences. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, wee are to expreſſe the nature of our propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, from the nature and exigency of the place of the Miniſtery. It is the complaint of learned and religious Biſhop <hi>Davenant, Imperita plebecula feriari nos arbitratur totos dies, nec aliquid negotii habere poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Templo pedem extulerimus:</hi> The ignorant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people imagineth that wee make many holi-dayes, and that wee have nothing to doe but onely at Church.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, our caſe is cleane otherwiſe; for beſides the outward exerciſe of our Paſtorall function, behold, there is, of not a perpetuall, yet a daily burden of prayer, meditation, ſtudy, &amp;c. Impoſed upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſhoulders; ſo that the truth is, wee never loyter leſſe, then when wee are thought to be moſt at leaſure.</p>
            <p>It is impoſſible to ſuſtaine theſe &amp; ſundry other paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full incumbencies, proper to our places without ſufficiencie, and affluence of competent mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>The want of this, may well occaſion the Clergy to impute the fault of fayling in theſe duties unto the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the times, and the penuriouſneſſe of the people, euen as victorious <hi>Annibal</hi> cryed out, <hi>negando ſupple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, vos retraxiſtis,</hi> how he was perforce drawn out of almoſt Conquered <hi>Jtaly,</hi> by the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27872:12"/>parſimony.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If ver erat aeternum, per ſe dabat omnia t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llus:</hi> the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den age were ſtill in <hi>eſſe,</hi> with a free will offering of all delights and neceſſaries. If bread and fiſh rained volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily downe from Heaven, as is reported to have fallen in the dayes of the Emperour <hi>Otho</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>Were the doctrine of the Iewiſh <hi>Talmud,</hi> verified for the preſent in this Iland, touching the free and ready preparedneſſe of all manner of Victuals. Could wee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to have the Angels our Caters with the Heremite <hi>Or</hi> in the deſert of <hi>Thebaies:</hi> or with another fabulous bird of the ſame feather Saint <hi>Alpias,</hi> to live a longer ſpace here on earth without hunger and thirſt.</p>
            <p>Were wee able to walke as farre with bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> went 1 <hi>Kings,</hi> 19. Or might our poore and ſmall meaſure of proviſion miraculouſly multiply like the Widdows little cruſe of oyle, and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of meale into many indeficient veſſels 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17. and 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Or would a few loaves and fiſhes ſuffice to feed thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and increaſe into ſundry basketfuls of fragments <hi>Matthew</hi> 14. Could our cloathes (like the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in their forty yeares travaile through the deſerts) continue without waxing old upon us, and our ſhooes hold good without waſt and decay on our feete, <hi>Deuterono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> 29.</p>
            <p>If a <hi>Manna</hi> honey-dew could ſtill bee gathered, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the terme of our mortall pilgrimage: or ſuch a ſweete ſhowre did mellifluouſly drop upon our drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſpirits, as <hi>Antoninus</hi> affirmeth to have deſcended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Chriſtian Hoſt, marching out of <hi>Antioch</hi> againſt the cruell <hi>Turke Corbonach,</hi> whereby a cheerefull vigour of minde and body, confirmed them in all the occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of that dangerous expedition.</p>
            <p>Were wee Chameleon complexion'd to feed on the ayre; or mouthleſſe like the Indian <hi>Aſtomi,</hi> to live by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27872:12"/>odour; Then ſhould Sacrilegious depredation and ſpoile bee borne with more patience, and not bring ſo much harme and prejudice. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, whereas (contrary to Anabaptiſts humours, who abide no Books but the Bible, &amp; ſome of them not ſo much as that) a good Library is the moſt neceſſary Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin &amp; ſtorehouſe, for to make meete proviſion of Sacred food for mens ſoules.</p>
            <p>Yea alſo to diſcover and diſcomfit the wilde Boares of the wood, the ravenous Wolues, and crafty Foxes; namely Tyrants, Machiavellians, Infidels, Heretiques, Hypocrites, Profaniſtes, Schiſmatiques, which continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally watch occaſion to ſurprize, worry, and devoure the Flocke. Were now as eaſie and cheape a way at our wiſhes, to get this ſame needfull company of meete Bookes; as we reade how once a Ship came floating into <hi>Alexandria</hi> of the owne accord full fraught with Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour to furniſh their wants.</p>
            <p>Or were not the expenſive precepts of Hoſpitality and almes deeds, of neceſſity to bee performed for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of dutie and example to the flocke.</p>
            <p>Or would the Almighty and moſt glorious God, the bountifull giver of all Majeſtie, riches and honour, the benigne beſtower of all pretious bleſſings well pleaſe and take it, that even not ſeldome in an ordinary mans houſe there appeares a ſtately ſtructure, a faire Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board of plate, a ſumptuous furniture, a coſtly table, a ſeemly attendance, a ſtable of good Geldings, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And yet will hee bee contented that his divine houſe ſhall remaine, in as bad condition many times as a ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſordid, and confuſed cottage; with a courſe carpet, a home ſpunne cloath to cover his holy-board, with a poore Parſonage, a beggarly Vicaridge, a thred-bare coate, a hungry table &amp;c. With the worſt and moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe tith for his tenthes; with poverty, neglect, and baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27872:13"/>for his Service and Miniſters?</p>
            <p>Doe ye thus requite the Lord, oh fooliſh people and unwiſe: <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> 32? Is this unworthy and blind partialty agreeable to the due of his glory, to the dignity of Chriſtian ſoules, to the direction of Eccleſiaſticall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, to the excellency of the Clergies profeſſion, to the credit of our Religion?</p>
            <p>Or were theſe and the like particulars, impropriate upon our owne private reſpects, and not chiefely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the honour of God, the propagation of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, the welfare of the people?</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Barbarus has ſegetes,</hi> we could the better ſuffer with wronged <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> the Sacrilegious <hi>Ziba</hi> to take all. Then tithes, oblations, and glebes might bee detracted from the Clergy, with a great deale leſſe griefe and injury to themſelves, alſo with much ſmaller harme and inconvenience to their Cures.</p>
            <p>But now ſince proportionable meanes are the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nerves of proceeding forward in every function: ſince money is the requiſite fountaine, which feedeth with her ſupplementall waters each river of humane actions and temporall affaires.</p>
            <p>Certainely then the Prieſtes Office muſt never bee grudged, nor depri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed of that like proviſionall priviledge and allowance which indeed wee uſe not to deny our ſelves, nor others in the exerciſe of inferiour profeſſions of farre ſmaller conſequences; yea wee ought to afford, what is requiſite in this kinde unto our very labouring beaſts. For, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the oxe that treadeth out the corne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, we are to declare the trueth of this doctrin, from the duneſſe of tithes by divine right to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Sundry well devoted children of the Church, Clergie and Laity have religiouſly laboured in this laudable ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Their lines to this purpoſe would ſhine as moſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:27872:13"/>cleare and reſplendent lights, did not miſerable men when light is come into the world, love darkneſſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then light. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Nothing hindereth a good cauſe more from prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, then the perverſe unconſcionableneſſe of covetous minded people, oppoſing the right for their owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. Commeth not this hence, of the evill luſts that warre in their members, <hi>Iames</hi> 4.5.</p>
            <p>And becauſe this naturall corruption, is the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of ſundrie folkes wilful contradiction, I ſuppoſe one ſtrong argument for the dueneſſe of tithes by divine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, might aptly be fetched forth in that regard.</p>
            <p>Surely, when as men are bound to honour the Lord with their ſubſtance. <hi>Proverbes</hi> 3. But they are bold to breake this bleſſed Commandement, and uſually preferre their wealth in the place of God, I mervaile not for my part, why the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hath named covetouſneſſe Idolatry.</p>
            <p>Although then I had much rather referre you to the excellent labours of others: Nevertheleſſe, ſince this particular is propounded among the reſt for confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our collected doctrine: It ſeemes beſt not to paſſe it over in ſilence, but to afford it a briefe diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Let us then ſpeake a litle in this caſe of tiths. Firſt, touching their primary intimation, and inſtitution in the old Teſtament. Secondly, concerning their poſteriour continuation under the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Firſt, touching the primary intimation, and inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of tiths in the old Teſtament. Before the Law, men having not the Law, were a law unto themſelves, and ſhewed the worke of the Law in their hearts, <hi>Romanes,</hi> 2. Many things were preſcribed in the times of <hi>Moſes</hi> by direct injunction, which were practiſed of holy men ſaith <hi>Pererins,</hi> long afore that ſeaſon, by a naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and by divine inſpiration. The <hi>Iewes</hi> (I have read) ſuppoſed the oblations of <hi>Cain</hi> not to have beene accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:27872:14"/>unto God, forſomuch as the eares which he tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, were penurious and not repleniſhed. <hi>Tertullian</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that <hi>Cains</hi> offering met with diſeſteeme, becauſe <hi>quod offerebat non recte dividebat,</hi> he dealt it not rightly. But whether hee offended in the number or nature, in the manner or meaſure, or in all; I imagine not ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to determine preciſely.</p>
            <p>It is enough for proofe of the point, that wee muſt know, even when the Church was in her Infancy, yet then before the Law, <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> were inſtructed (either by tradition, or elſe by naturall reaſon) that a chief part of whatſoever the earth yielded unto them, was payable to the Lords peculiar worſhip.</p>
            <p>The next piece of antiquity to our purpoſe, appeareth in the memorable paſſages between <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hiſedech;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: The Patriarch with a hearty freeneſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided unto him a tenth part of al, yea even of the ſpoiles; and the Prieſt tithed him as having authority.</p>
            <p>The concluſion is demonſtrative from the type to the truth, from <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the one is transferred into the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> upon this other. As bleſſing then, and tithing were extant in the Prieſthood of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech,</hi> ſo are they moſt evident in the Prieſthood of Chriſt: which ſhall more appeare hereafter.</p>
            <p>As all ſinned in the loines of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo all are tithed in the loines of <hi>Abraham, Lyra</hi> affirmeth. Behold this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch who had the promiſes, did by this his action bind all his ſeed, both the children of his fleſh and the children of his faith.</p>
            <p>It then we will be happily taken up; into his Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall boſome after our bodily diſſolution, wee muſt alſo make him a Father of our thankfulneſſe: if wee receive bleſſings in him, we ought not refuſe to pay tiths in him. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Old <hi>Jacobs</hi> turne is next: obſerve (as the learned thinke) that his Viſion concerneth his whole poſterity.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27872:14"/>It followeth then (they inferre) that his vow of giving ſurely the Tenth unto God, is no leſſe largely obligato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, yea upon all the families of the earth to bee bleſſed in his ſeed, <hi>Geneſis.</hi> 28. The two former points of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> vow; namely, firſt that the Lord ſhould bee his God. Secondly, how that Pillar ſhould be Gods Houſe, paſſe without controverſie to bee perpetuall, touching a generall foundation of Religion, and of Sacred houſes for divine exerciſes.</p>
            <p>But the third particular of conferring tiths to the Lords worſhip and Service, meeteth with much excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt all good reaſon; becauſe what would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the two other, if this latter did not ſupply libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall maintenance?</p>
            <p>The Lord ſaith <hi>Ferus,</hi> needed none of <hi>Iacobs</hi> gifts, nevertheleſſe the holy Patriarch knew it was his duty to conferre toward the maintenance of his divine Service and worſhip; although the precept of tithing was not yet extant, yet the law of nature did dictate that wee ought liberally to contribute unto theſe Sacred perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances out of our proper goods and ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the Prieſts amongſt the Gentiles had in all places a liberall ſuſtentation and reſpect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jacob</hi> hee concludeth appeareth herein, to bee much more piouſly perfect then we are; loe he long afore the written Law unconſtrained, of his owne free will, vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth tiths unto God. But wee are ſo far remote off from his devotion, that in ſtead of paying wee purloine them, in lieu of giving we take away.</p>
            <p>Now if any one he addeth, be forward to reply, That the law of tithes did appertaine unto the old Teſtament, and ſo it is now abrogated; he anſwereth how the law of nature ſtandeth ſtill in vigour, which requireth no leſſe then the performance of our Doctrine. Alſo he ſaith how the law of charity ought to bee of that force, as to give more then the tenths in the times of neceſſity: yea
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:27872:15"/>if occaſion urgeth the whole for Chriſts ſake, who hath given himſelfe wholy for us.</p>
            <p>Neither (as Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> noteth) doth our <hi>Jacobs</hi> vow at this preſent intimate any neglect of this duty in him before, ſince it is lawfull for a Chriſtian to tie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by a new vow to performe that unto God, which he is otherwiſe bound to accompliſh, and hath bin wont to put in practiſe. For by theſe meanes we may whet and better our weake and dull devotions.</p>
            <p>Finally, the queſtion here moved by ſome diſaffected folkes unto the Church: To whom <hi>Iacob</hi> paid his tiths? ſeemes unneceſſary, and indeed not mannerly dealing with the divine word. <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Heber</hi> ſuppoſed by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry to bee the men, deceaſed long before: But the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, the ſacrifice, the worſhip, the ſervice of Almighty God (who liveth for ever) were the objects of our thankfull Patriarchs pious vow: And this hee performed unto the Lord, whiles he conſecrated the tenth part of his goods unto religious uſes. <hi>Cajetan</hi> and <hi>Mercer</hi> conſent to this purpoſe. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the oxe &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tithes and the Law were not twinnes of one time. <hi>Brentius</hi> noteth them for no new invention of the Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Prieſts, but a thing long before accuſtomed of the Patriarchs, in way of thankſgiving and devotion.</p>
            <p>Yea the very Gentiles, ſome by the light of nature, ſome by tradition from the ſonnes of <hi>Noah;</hi> held this for a principle: That they were bound to honour the al-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God with their riches; whereupon many of them paid tiths.</p>
            <p>Thus the Law was but a confirmer, and <hi>Levi</hi> but an obſerver of that maintenance long afore offered, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted unto divine Services. Therefore theſe tenths are fondly by ſome imagined to bee ceremoniall, and by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers judiciall. The men of this world make them any thing, with a mind to pay nothing: but from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:27872:15"/>it was not ſo. <hi>Matthew</hi> 19. The firſt borne were then the Prieſts, and they received tiths due to the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. As ſoone as that Sacred name is ſpoken of in the holy Scripture, behold there likewiſe mentioned the payment of tiths, that calling brought on that conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the Prieſthood and tiths ſeeme things reciprocate. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſame divinely inſpired practiſe did afterward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed into precept. We may heare Almighty God, not in a ſenſe of generality, but in a ſignification of ſpeciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, claiming them as his owne origin all right. <hi>Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> 27. <hi>And all the tiths of the Land, whether of the ſeed of the Land, or of the fruit of the tree, is the Lords: It is holy unto the Lord. And concerning the tiths of the herd, or of the flocke, even of whatſoever paſſeth under the rod, the tenth ſhall be holy unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the place concludeth tiths Gods proper right, and royall revenue. Hee hath a common right moſt amply diffuſed in regard of his creation and providence: Every beaſt of the Forreſt, and the cattle upon a thouſand hils, the foules of the mountaine, and the wilde beaſts of the field. <hi>Pſame,</hi> 50. All are his, and hold of his good pleaſure.</p>
            <p>But he hath a ſpeciall right unto tiths as his own reſerved demeanes: they belong to his Majeſtie independantly: ſo they were ſolemnely proclaimed in <hi>Sinai</hi> above twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeeres at leaſt afore their aſſignation to the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it appeareth, although he had not appointed them to have beene their portion, yet had they beene ſtill his: he vouchſafeth (Maſter <hi>Calvins</hi> phraſe is) to ſubſtitute or ſurrogate them into his owne place touching the tiths: hee addeth how <hi>Abraham</hi> paid into the hands of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> what indeed be ought unto God.</p>
            <p>Our due acknowledgement of all fruites and increaſe to come from the Lords goodneſſe, is witneſſed by our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:27872:16"/>tribute of tithes to him, which when he demandeth he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth not ours, but his owne.</p>
            <p>The moſt gracious God hath beene pleaſed to make a deputation of this right, to ſuch perſons who miniſter unto him in holy things, throughout all ages, as wel afore <hi>Moſes,</hi> as under the time of his Law, moreover in the ſucceeding ſeaſon of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>So that what his Majeſtie proclaimed, <hi>Numbers</hi> 18. <hi>Behold, J have given the children of Levi all the tenth in Iſrael for an inheritance, for their ſervice which they ſerve, even the Service of the Tabernacle of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation;</hi> It appertaineth unto the whole company of his Prieſts whiles the world endureth in reſpect of their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred imployment.</p>
            <p>Although God gave the tiths to the <hi>Levites,</hi> yet did he not firſt found them in that Incorporation, but onely transferred his owne right to that order, ſo long as it ſhould continue. And after that expired, loe the ſame right deſcended (as it were by entaile) to the ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miniſtery of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Since then the Lords certaine right, and demaund of tithes hath been openly confirmed by his owne publique Statute: And ſince that his good pleaſure hath ſolemnly appointed them for the holy Service ſake, unto his divine Miniſters in all times.</p>
            <p>How dareth then the contemptible creature diſanull the decrees of the incomprehenſible Creatour? What a marvelous impudency ſeemeth it in humane mortality to tranſmute the ordinances of the omnipotent Majeſty?</p>
            <p>How audacious doth the vile duſt of man appeare, for to vary and alter the celeſtiall Lawes of his unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble maker? Loe, he hath required the tenth, but where did he ever remit it? Hee hath bound us in the obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his precept, but where did he ever cancel it?</p>
            <p>Why preſumeth any one to uſurpe upon an impious liberty, when as his Highneſſe hath vouchſafed no privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:27872:16"/>nor licence? <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the oxe &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tiths ſeeme neither Ceremoniall nor Iudiciall, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther typicall nor civill.</p>
            <p>Touching the former: no proofe is made of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute: the ceremonies of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law were ſo ordained, as they did prefigure, and were ſimilitudes of heavenly things, ſtanding in meates, and drinkes, and divers waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and carnall rites, untill the time of reformation. <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 9. and they lived no longer, then whiles Chriſt came, unto whom they looked.</p>
            <p>But neyther had tithes any ceremoniall inſtitution, being ſeparated for the neceſſary uſe and maintenance of the <hi>Levites:</hi> neither though they looked toward Chriſt, did they breath their laſt gaſpe at his bleſſed birth, for then might the morall Lawes have alſo expired at the ſame period.</p>
            <p>Touching the latter: they ſeeme no Iudicials, for they concerned properly the Common-wealth, and theſe were peculiar to the Prieſt-hood: they pertained to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, theſe to piety: they were no Iudges of things Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotall and ſacred, theſe had an Eccleſiaſticall nature, and a being afore the order of <hi>Levi,</hi> and the time of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was taken notice of.</p>
            <p>They are conſecrate to God, man may not meddle with them, but onely by vertue of his Soveraigne right: when men make uſe of them, as of the Lords allowance or wages: marke then, that this is not for our naturall or civill worke, but for Religion, the divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>Wherefore we muſt not imagine the tenths as things in common uſe, but ſeparate by God himſelfe for his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſervice and ſervants, ſo they ought to continue without humane reverſall.</p>
            <p>For what the Lord hath once eſtabliſhed, and enacted, and limited within the liſtes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no expreſſe ſpace of time;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:27872:17"/>Behold, that muſt remaine, as the laſting of the Lawes of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> are anciently written of, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable for ever, untill the ſame God himſelfe doth repeale them, who at firſt ratified them.</p>
            <p>Whiles his divine Service endureth, the tiths which are appropriate to him, and thereunto deputed by him, muſt likewiſe keepe their courſe of continuance. Surely, they which vainely ſuppoſe, that his ſoveraigne ſtatutes may be dealt with like a noſe of wax, or a leaden rule, namely altered and wreſted according to covetous mens corrupt humours, ſhall verily finde him at length to <hi>breaks them with a rod of iron, and to daſh them in pieces like a potters veſſell: Pſam.</hi> 2. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, concerning the Poſteriour continuation of the right of tiths under the Goſpell: that may be entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of in this twofold manner: namely, either by divine conſtitution, or elſe by humane conſecration.</p>
            <p>Firſt, touching the continuation of the right of the tiths under the Goſpell, by divine conſtitution. It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, <hi>Gualter</hi> writeth to know, that the duties paya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of old in this kinde, ought to be transferred unto the Church of the New Teſtament. For although the Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Prieſthood be aboliſhed, and legall ſacrifices have ceaſed; yet notwithſtanding the miniſtery of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ſtill remaineth, and therefore the meanes of their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving muſt in no wiſe be diminiſhed.</p>
            <p>Some of the learned have alledged in this ſenſe, our Saviour Chriſts anſwere <hi>Matthew</hi> 22. When as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull Phariſees ſought ſo ſubtilly to circumvent him; Render (ſaith he) to <hi>Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and unto God the things that are Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> muſt receive his tribute according to the image ſuperſcribed upon the coine, God muſt receive his claime according to the purport of his Law in that caſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:27872:17"/>
            <p>Wee reade in the 23. Chapter of the ſame Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, how our Lord Ieſus reproving the hypocriſie of the Scribes and Phariſees, for making a goodly ſhew of an upright conſcience in their tithing, even of the ſmalleſt particulars, when as they omitted the weightier matters of the Law; loe he doth thus at laſt conclude, Theſe ought yee to have done, and not to leave the other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine, Chryſoſtome,</hi> with ſundry famous Authours beſides expound this inſtance to our purpoſe. I mervaile then, how a great many miſerable Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wormes moſt vainely imagine to mount up aloft, into the heaven of bliſſe, comming very farre ſhort of the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees in this caſe; when as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>except your righteouſneſſe ſhall exceede the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, yee ſhall in no wiſe enter into the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is their cavill of any ſufficient force, how the alledged place onely concerned the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> under the <hi>Levite</hi> Prieſthood; Becauſe as the Lord Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes</hi> obſerveth, whereas other Phariſaicall ſcrupuloſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties premiſed in the chapter meet with a brand of abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this ſtill remaineth with a mark of approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Neither dare I ſuppoſe, that the intereſt of the Lord ſolemnely eſtabliſhed in the old Teſtament, doth thus ſodamely expire in the New, unleſſe his owne ſelfe had ſignified unto us a reſignation of his right.</p>
            <p>It is written <hi>Matthew.</hi> 11. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erily I ſay unto you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that are borne of women, there hath not riſen a greater then John the Baptiſt: notwithſtanding hee that is leaſt in the Kingdome of heaven, is greater then hee.</hi> Meaning, that for ſo much as <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt was next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt in time, above all the Prophets, which ever li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before him, his happineſſe went therefore beyond
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:27872:18"/>them in that high reſpect for he ſaw what they deſired to ſee, and ſaw not.</p>
            <p>Becauſe alſo he was of a more worthy calling, for hee might be reported to have pointed out Chriſt with the finger of a fuller diſcovery, which others could not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry, but onely afarre off.</p>
            <p>Thus likewiſe thoſe men which ſucceeded <hi>John</hi> in this ſacred Miniſtery, namely the Apoſtle, and their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours to the end of the world, are happier in a higher degree, and of a more excellent calling then <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, becauſe living in the reſplendent ſeaſon of the much gloriouſer illumination of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Downham</hi> examining the particulars of the <hi>Levites</hi> profits, affirmeth, how they amounted to a far greater meaſure for the maintenance of that ſmall tribe, then all the Biſhoprickes, Benefices, Colledgelands, or whatſoever other Eccleſiaſticall emoluments doe yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, yea although the Index <hi>expurgatorius</hi> of ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inquiſition had not with that extreme tyranny in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded, and over-runne them.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould then the Evangelicall Sunne ſo marvei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly ſurmounting the glimmering Moone ſhine of the Law, in the ſweet of ſaving knowledge, ſuffer ſo miſſebe-ſeeming an eclipſe in the moſt diſproportionable meanes of Miniſterial maintenance, &amp; not rather exceed the other in neceſſary abundance, as it doth in notable brightneſſe?</p>
            <p>If the miniſtration of condemnation be glorious, much more doth the miniſtration of righteouſneſſe exceede in glory. 2 <hi>Corinthians.</hi> 3. when as the Miniſter of the Goſpell hath ſucceeded the <hi>Levite</hi> in the Miniſtery, and is the Miniſter of a better Teſtament, what cauſe can bee then conceived, but that he ought alſo to ſucceed him in the ſtipend or allowance?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quatis ratio ſpraecepti tale praeceptum:</hi> the Civilians tell us, it is right that the Law ſhould not expire as long as the reaſon of it remaineth. Moreover reaſon, equity,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:27872:18"/>and ſacred Scripture requite, that the worthier wages belong to the worthier Calling. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further obſerve how the 13. and 14. verſes of this Chapter, as likewiſe <hi>Galatians</hi> 6. will (if well conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) that the decree touching tiths in the old Teſtament is not diſſolved in the new, but ſtill continued, and the practiſe of the former a preſident for the latter.</p>
            <p>For that ſame maintenance which the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in thoſe places maketh mention of, is moſt aptly expounded by Scripture to be the tenth part.</p>
            <p>And though the manner of portion in them places, ſeeme in ſome mens ſight left undetermined, yet if wee may explaine Scripture by Scripture (as indeede ſuch a mutuall intercourſe ſhould bee betweene the old and new Teſtament) then doubtleſſe the cleare phraſes of the one may eaſily declare the obſcurer ſpeech of the other: And ſo by the context of holy writ the tenth will ſoone come to bee diſcovered, and Gods ordinance there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated by the Apoſtle, be preſerved inviolable, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conceits without warrant, be diſcarded, and this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Law endure in force and vigour. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeventh Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> ſeemeth a ſtrong champion in this caſe. Now conſider how great this man was, unto whom even the Patriarch <hi>Abraham</hi> gave the tenth of the ſpoiles.</p>
            <p>And verily they that are of the ſonnes of <hi>Levi,</hi> who receive the Office of the Prieſthood, have a commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to take tiths of the people, according to the Law, that is of their brethren, though they came out of the loines of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he whoſe deſcent is not counted from them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived tiths of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and bleſſed him that had the promiſes.</p>
            <p>And without all contradiction the leſſe is bleſſed of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27872:19"/>the better. And here men that die receive tiths, but there he receiveth them of whom it is witneſſed that hee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth. And as I may ſo ſay, <hi>Levi</hi> alſo who received tiths, paid tiths in <hi>Abraham.</hi> For hee was yet in the loines of his Father when <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> met him. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Levi in Abraham decimatus eſt, quoniam in lumbis ejus fuit, quando decimas dedit ſacerdoti Melchiſedech:</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtin</hi> hath left written that <hi>Levi</hi> was tithed in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> becauſe he was in his loines, when he gave tiths to the Prieſt <hi>Melchiſedech.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conceive the ſcope of this Scripture is to manifeſt, and magnifie the high and honourable condition of <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech,</hi> and conſequently of Chriſt Ieſus. But one maine argument for <hi>Melchiſedecs</hi> admirable greatneſſe, is drawne by our Apoſtle from his receiving tiths of him, whoſe off-ſpring the tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> (then in <hi>Abrahams</hi> loines) afterwards tooke tiths.</p>
            <p>For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he tithed <hi>Abraham,</hi> taking the tenth part of him as his due, and not given.</p>
            <p>Neither may wee affirme that <hi>Melchiſedecs</hi> admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble greatneſſe is ſince unhappily eclipſed, and fallen into wane, but rather he is as ample and evident ſtill as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he was, becauſe he is the Prieſt of God for ever, a Prieſt that never dieth; and ſo his Prieſthood and the rights of it never ceaſe.</p>
            <p>But certainely his greatneſſe in his antitype Chriſt, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be concluded to be ſtill the ſame, if Chriſt hath no right to take tiths, for this indeed appeareth the chiefeſt, and moſt urged of the two notable arguments to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>This argument of <hi>Pererius</hi> may bee ſaid to concerne the point; The Prieſthood of <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> hath beene more excellent then the Leviticall Prieſthood. But Chriſt hath beene a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech:</hi> therefore the Prieſthood of Chriſt is more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:27872:19"/>then the Leviticall Prieſthood.</p>
            <p>The minor propoſition is manifeſt, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 110. and the major is proved by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in a twofold manner, partly becauſe <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> bleſſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe he received tiths of him.</p>
            <p>What then was due and paid to <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> is alſo due and payable to Chriſt, elſe he were not a Prieſt for ever after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> if he ſhould faile in ſomething to be as <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was: But to grant that ſeemeth abſurd, becauſe he is after his order, as the Prieſts of the Law were after <hi>Aarons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since then tiths were due and paid to <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> doubtleſſe they are due and ought to be paid unto Chriſt: And ſo conſequently to his ſervants the Miniſters of the Goſpell, who are Chriſt repreſentatively, and in whom he bleſſeth, &amp; refreſheth with the bread and wine of the holy Sacrament, &amp; of heavenly conſolations the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which are weary and ready otherwiſe to ſaint in their ſpirituall warrefare.</p>
            <p>Neither was <hi>Abrahams</hi> payment of tiths voluntary, but of duty: for were muſt note how <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was the image of Chriſt &amp; his Church: <hi>Abraham</hi> figured forth the Congregation of the faithfull.</p>
            <p>Although then <hi>Levi</hi> received tiths afterward by a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular grant from God for the time, yet he payd them ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally with the Congregation in the loines of <hi>Abraham</hi> unto the Prieſthood of Chriſt, here perſoned by <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech:</hi> which being perpetuall, and an image of this in the Goſpell, may well note unto us, that this duty of tithing ought alſo to be perpetuall.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> conceiveth <hi>Abraham</hi> to have been herein our Tutour; and whiles he payeth tiths, not to a Prieſt offering up Leviticall ſacrifices, but adminiſtring bread and wine (the elements of the Evangelicall Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) it intimateth ſufficiently that men muſt now pay their tiths to the Miniſters of the Goſpell.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:27872:20"/>
            <p>Moreover, if the order of Prieſthood here ſpoken of be an eternall order, and yet ſuch an order as to whom the tiths are due (which plainly appeareth in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alledged) ſurely then, let the Prieſt be either <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech</hi> the type, or Chriſt the Antitype, yet the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter muſt remaine ſtill evinced, namely that tiths muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies continue to the end of the world, being the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full due of an enduring Prieſthood.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe may be applyed theſe words of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Calvin</hi> on the place; The Apoſtle affirmeth the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>Melchiſedechs</hi> Prieſthood to be for ever, and that of the Prieſthood of <hi>Levi</hi> but temporary. The life of this latter Prieſthood was one day to be diſſolved, even as the lives of men liquid expire.</p>
            <p>Yet no Scripture ſpeaking of tiths payd to <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech,</hi> ſaith any thing of his death, wherefore the right of his Prieſthood was not to ceaſe but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.</p>
            <p>The latter Law did not derogate from the former, the right belonging of old to <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> is not now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed by another Law given of God by <hi>Moſes,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to turne over that right unto the <hi>Levites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> prevented that conceit, <hi>cum dicit ad tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus decimas Levitis ſolutas,</hi> ſhewing that tiths were paid to the <hi>Levites</hi> but for a certaine ſeaſon, becauſe they might not live ever.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> being immortall, retaineth unto the end what God hath once given him; namely the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, duty, yea and the rights of the Prieſthood, which are declared to be the tiths, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The 13.14. &amp;c. verſes of this 7. Chapter with ſome other paſſages therein, will determine the things ſpoken under the name of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> upon Chriſt without queſtion.</p>
            <p>Behold then he is the rightfull receiver of tiths, in his Evangelicall Prieſthood, even by witneſſe of the new Teſtament.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:27872:20"/>
            <p>As under the Law tiths were not ſo much the <hi>Levites</hi> at Gods in the <hi>Levites,</hi> they receiving them as deputed by him to take this ſacred tribute.</p>
            <p>Even ſo likewiſe before the Law, not ſo much <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech,</hi> as the Lord in <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> did receive tiths. Now under the Goſpell, not ſo much the Miniſters of the Goſpell, as he that is our bleſſed Lord Ieſus Chriſt in the Miniſters of the Goſpell, doth by divine right take the tithes.</p>
            <p>Miſerable then are thoſe wretches which dare defraud him, by depriving his Miniſters, and regard not this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although whiles Chriſt lived on earth, the Leviticall Prieſthood being not abrogated, had the tithes. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over he and his Apoſtles leading a kinde of travelling life from place to place, could not conveniently receive them; yet intermiſſion for a time muſt not bee thought to infringe their due right; no more then the ſuſpenſion of circumciſion for forty yeares ſpace in the wilderneſſe, did diſannull that.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles alſo and their primitive ſucceſſours tooke the price of whole fields, and poſſeſſions of thoſe which converted to the Church, and profeſſed the Goſpell; whereby they had meete meanes to maintaine their owne ſelves, and the poore brethren.</p>
            <p>That courſe continued about two hundred yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, and the practiſe of it multiplied into a very great proportion.</p>
            <p>Then the ſtate of the Church being ſetled, the ancient Fathers taught tithes to be thus due, general councels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed them ſo, and publique authority renewed the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe the Lord Biſhop <hi>Andrewes</hi> bringeth in <hi>Cyprian, Clemens Alexandrinus, Origen, Auguſtin, Chryſoſtome, Hierome, &amp;c.</hi> Pronouncing the detainers of tithes to be invaders of other mens goods: how ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:27872:21"/>leſſe nor worſe muſt be paid: how the offenders in this ſort have no due feare of God, not true ſenſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance;</p>
            <p>Yea to be voyd of all thankfull memory, of the divine liberality and bounty to wards them. How ſuch wretches ſeeme wickeder then the Scribes and Phariſees, who durſt meddle with nothing for their proper uſes, before they had firſt of all ſeparated the tenthes, fearing elſe a curſe to fall upon them for defrauding the Lord.</p>
            <p>He alſo produceth ſome Orthodox Councels, which ſtrictly decreed <hi>decimarum penſiones et paraeciarum divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones,</hi> the payments of tithes and diviſions of Pariſhes: Alſo ſhew the ordinances of divine Lawes in this caſe, and the Excommunication of refractory offenders in this point.</p>
            <p>Hee alſo rehearſeth ſome inſtances out of the Canon and Civill Lawes, which anciently accounted Pariſhes and tithes, Clergie and tenths &amp;c. to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procate and convertible, and they did enjoyne the true payments of them under extreme penalties.</p>
            <p>Neither did ſundry old conſtitutions, provide onely for honeſt dealing in prediall tithes, but alſo their care extended to have thoſe which are of a perſonall nature to be well paid. They had in conſcience a notable ground for this, out of that memorable place: <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>From which <hi>Aquinas</hi> affirmeth, how all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever a man poſſeſſeth, be contained under the carnall things mentioned by the Apoſtle, and therefore hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferteth that tithes ought to be paid out of all our goods &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus much was worthily projected in the raigne of our late King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, and more largely delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated &amp; allowed by many of the Lords ſpirituall &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, beſides ſundry other eminent perſons, when the laſt <hi>Edward</hi> ſweyghed our Engliſh Scepter: who (as Maſter
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:27872:21"/>
               <hi>Studley</hi> writeth) willingly confirmed this religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, juſt, and neceſſary reſolution, for all men of traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke, ſciences, trades, &amp;c. that they ſhould put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe the cuſtome of the City of London, for the payment of perſonall tithes: Alledging there could be no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for Farmours, Plowmen, Shepheards, &amp;c. to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne the tenth, and nevertheleſſe that the perſons of this gainfull condition would preſume themſelves to be free and exempted.</p>
            <p>It ſeemes then an imagination voyd of all true conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and devotion (whether we examine it by the light of nature, or by the brightneſſe of grace) for any people to pretend, and plead an immunity, from liberall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing to the maintenance of their ſpirituall Paſtours. It is alſo irreverently oppoſit againſt the opinion and practiſe of venerable antiquity, and contrary to my text. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally if the words of a few, otherwiſe ſuppoſing Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors (whether grave divines or judicious Lawyers bee well pondered) I conceive in effect they ſpeake to the point, I am ſure to the purpoſe of my text.</p>
            <p>For all of them unanimouſly plead againſt wronging the Church, and for a liberall allowance to the Clergy, to furniſh and maintaine themſelves and their families, to keepe hoſpitality, to relieve the poore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solutio decimarum Sacerdotibus eſt de jure divino, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus inde ſuſtentantur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gerſon,</hi> they hold them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely precepted in theſe reſpects.</p>
            <p>Yea, the Doctor and Student acknowledge it, to bee grounded upon the law of reaſon, that every one is bound to honour God of his proper ſubſtance, by giving a meet portion of his temporall goods unto the Miniſter, to him of things ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>That treatiſe further affirmeth, how there is no cauſe why the people of the new Law ought to pay leſſe, to the Miniſters of the new Law, then the people of the old
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27872:22"/>Teſtament gave to the Miniſters of the old Teſtament. For the people of the new Law, bee bound to greater things then the people of the old Law were: <hi>Matthew</hi> 5. And the ſacrifice of the old Law was not ſo honorable as the ſacrifice of the new Law is. For the ſacrifice of the old Law was onely the figure, but the ſacrifice of the new Law is the thing that is figured: that was the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, this is the truth.</p>
            <p>To conclude, moſt of them commend the old tithing courſe: Inſomuch as no few of theſe profeſſe in Maſter <hi>Perkins</hi> ſpeeches; doubtleſſe had not God himſelfe in the old Teſtament taken ſuch ſtrict orders for the livings of the <hi>Levites,</hi> they had beene put to no leſſe extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, then is the miniſtery of this age, which is many times ſo miſerably muzzeled, as no mercifull man would ſuffer his beaſt. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the oxe that treadeth out the corne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, touching the continuation of the tithes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpell by humane conſecration. Admit as ſome vainely ſurmiſe, that the payment of the tithes were meerely a Moſaicall mandate: from which men under the Goſpell are made free; yet becauſe nature hath taught men to honour God with their ſubſtance: and for that the moſt true and ſure way to performe thus much, is by making and rendering him payment in kind, out of the very ſelfe ſame tiches, which through his gracious bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the earth continually bringeth forth.</p>
            <p>And ſince that beſides, Scripture hath left us an evident example of that particular proportion, which for morall conſiderations hath beene determined moſt fit and meet by them, whoſe wiſedome could beſt of all judge. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, ſeeing that the Church of Chriſt hath long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go entered into the like obligation of tithing; me thinks then in theſe daies this queſtion ſeemes vaine and ſuperfluous, whether tithes be due by divine right or no?</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:27872:22"/>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Downham</hi> accordingly declareth that tithes are due to Chriſtian Miniſters by vow: Chriſtian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales and Councels having conſecrated them to God, and his Church: neither is it now meet time, after vowes to make this manner of enquiry, nor to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for to alter them without divine diſpenſation and ſufficient ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>For grant at the firſt that it might have beene imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a doubtfull and diſputable matter, yet now our caſe appeareth to hold a cleare correſpondence with theirs unto whom Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake <hi>Actes</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whiles it remained, was it not thine owne? and after it was ſold, was it not in thine ewne power? Why haſt thou conceived this thing in thine heart? thou haſt not lyed unto men, but unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then it were not lawfull for <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> under pretence of Religion to ſell their Land, as if they would have given it to the Church, and yet concealed and detracted part thereof, for which we read their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible tragedy in the aforeſaid Chapter.</p>
            <p>Then is it much more unlawfull to detaine and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold any part from the Church, which wee never gave, but it was rightly the Churches juſt poſſeſſion before we were borne.</p>
            <p>The generall current of grave authority runneth this way, that whatſoever hath beene lawfully given to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, can never be taken away againe, unleſſe redeemed with a greater price, <hi>Leviticus</hi> 27.</p>
            <p>The reaſon is eaſily thus rendered, becauſe the goods of the Church are holy things, and therefore not to bee prophaned, which offence is then committed, when as they are withdrawne from the Lords Service.</p>
            <p>The 250 cenſers of the ſeditious ſinners. <hi>Numbers</hi> 16. might not be prophaned becauſe they had beene hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for by the Lords owne direction <hi>Moſes</hi> appointed <hi>Eleazar</hi> to take them out of the burning, and to make
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27872:23"/>of the broad plates for a covering to the Altar, alledging their conſecration and offering up before him.</p>
            <p>Neither can the evill lives of ſome Miniſters (much leſſe incroaching ſacriledge) juſtly alienate thoſe tithes, glebes and oblations, which have beene hallowed and offered up unto Gods Service.</p>
            <p>For certainely although in ſubſtance the tithes, the glebes, and other goods of the Church, ſeeme the ſame that all other are, out of which they he taken.</p>
            <p>As for example ſake, the water, the bread and the wine in the Sacraments, are all one with other water, bread, and wine; yet in regard of the uſe thereof, behold we muſt conceive no ſmall difference: ſince they are made holy and ſacred by dedication.</p>
            <p>Therefore as it were horrible villany to abuſe the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Sacraments: ſo is it execrable robbery to prophane the tithes, the glebes and other goods of the Church, and to pervert them from the religious end of their firſt inſtitution, unto ſecular (and ſo ſacrilegious) occaſions.</p>
            <p>The title and right then which man had in any of theſe things (which ſeemed in his owne arbittement either to give or reſerve) before his donation of them to the Church, doth by the act, and from the time of any ſuch dedication, remaine the proper poſſeſſion of God untill the worlds end, unleſſe himſelfe renounce or relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it.</p>
            <p>Good reaſon it ſhould be thus, ſince equity hath taught us, that every one ought to enjoy his owne, and what is ours no other can alienate from us, without our delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate conſent.</p>
            <p>No man having paſt his voluntary agreement or deed may at his pleaſure change it to the prejudice of another. Should wee then wickedly dare to deale worſe with our good God, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his gracious Majeſtie hath permitted any other men to deale with us? When our tithes &amp;c. might
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27872:23"/>probably have appeared our owne, wee had faire colour of liberty to uſe and diſpoſe them as our ſelves thought good; but having once made them his whoſe they are, having conſecrated them to his worſhip and Service; Let us wiſely be warned by other folkes fearefull exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, what a hainous crime it is, even but to waſh and clip that coine which carrieth on it the marke of God, the token of his divine inſculpture.</p>
            <p>Hee reckoneth all theſe by the forme of his owne ſpeeches for his owne poſſeſſions. It muſt needs then be a moſt dangerous matter for the children of men ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly to invade them, and to deſpoile his Miniſters (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom he hath deputed them) from the fruition of them. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover it ſeemes a point of no ſmall moment, and a thing very worthy our conſideration, that the true meaning of all ſuch as honoured the Lord with their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, was to inveſt him with the propriety of what they dedicated unto him.</p>
            <p>Witneſſe the ſtile of ancient grants. Thus in <hi>magna charta:</hi> wee have given unto God, both for us and our heires for ever. Thus <hi>Charles</hi> the Great; we know that the goods of the Church are the ſacred endowments of God: To the Lord our God we offer and dedicate what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we deliver unto his Church.</p>
            <p>Thus the Lawes Imperiall make ſome-things to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long by right of nature, indifferently to every man; ſome to be the certaine goods and poſſeſſions of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales, ſome to appertaine unto ſeverall Corporations and Companies, ſome to be privately mens owne in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; ſome to be ſeparate quite from all men.</p>
            <p>This laſt branch comprehendeth things ſacred and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe thereof God alone is owner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nullius autem ſunt res Sacrae, et religioſae, et Sanctae; quod enim divini juris eſt, id nullius in bonis eſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Sacred, religious and holy things can never bee in the right of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:27872:24"/>Lay-mens incroachment. That which is the Lords ought to be free from ſecular claime and uſurpation. Thus we might read in the Lawes of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great: There is not an Act more honourable, then by all meanes to defend and amplifie the patrimony of Religion: Nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more hatefull and impious Conſtitution, then to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire thoſe poſſeſſions, which devout men in former times, when they gave them unto holy uſes, were wont in the moſt ſolemne place of Gods Church, and in the preſence of their Ghoſtly Superiours, to make (as they thought) inviolable, by words of fearefull execration in this wiſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe things we offer to God, from whom, if any man take them away (which we hope no man will attempt to do.) But if any ſhall goe about it, let his account bee without favour in the laſt day, when he commeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the doome, which is due for ſacriledge againſt that Lord and God unto whom we dedicate the ſame.</p>
            <p>Oh conſider this ye that forget God and his Saints, in the frequency and ſenſeleſſeneſſe of this ſoule and curſed ſinne, leſt hee teare you in pieces, and there bee none to deliver.</p>
            <p>Thus the beſt and moſt renowned Prelates of the Church of Chriſt, have rather in this conſideration ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained the cruell wrath, then yielded to ſatisfie the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious deſire of their greateſt Commanders on earth, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veting by evill adviſe and Councell, that which moſt willingly they ſhould have ſuffered God to enjoy, &amp;c. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some perſon may chance move this queſtion; can the goods of the Church, theſe conſecrated things in no caſe be alienated? I anſwere, certaine cauſes there are, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is not obſcure, but the Lord himſelfe doth licenſe &amp; warrant how we may ſafely preſume him as willing to forgoe for our benefit, as alwaies to uſe and convert to our benefit, whatſoever our religion, hath honoured him withall.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:27872:24"/>
            <p>But here is an intollerable miſchiefe, under this may be, many things which by no meanes muſt be, paſſe for currant and without controll in this ſacrilegious world.</p>
            <p>We deny not but occaſions of many conſequence may ſometimes be incident, wherein the welfare and danger of the Church bee alſo involved with the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth occurrences. Wee alſo ſuppoſe the ſafety of the people in ſundry caſes to be a ſupreme Law.</p>
            <p>Wee know that Kings and Princes, are the breath of our Noſthrills: Wherefore Church &amp; Common-wealth muſt concurre in neceſſary care, and loyall duty towards them.</p>
            <p>Thus the learned apply theſe examples of <hi>Ahimelech</hi> the Prieſt, giving unto <hi>David</hi> the hallowed bread, &amp;c. Of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> giving the ſilves in the houſe of the Lord, and the gold of the doores of the Temple to <hi>Senacherib</hi> King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> for to purchaſe his owne, and people peace.</p>
            <p>Thus our Saviour Chriſt, in defence of his diſciples plucking the eares of corne &amp;c. alledgeth <hi>the Sabboth was made for man, and not man for the Sabboth Marke</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Thus Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did cauſe the very conſecrated veſſels of the Church to be broken and coined, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of the poore, in a time of extreme neceſſity and famine.</p>
            <p>After this manner the ancient Biſhop <hi>Acacius</hi> redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſeven thouſand captives, out of moſt miſerable bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. All which and the like ſavour of Chriſtian chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but they diſſent from the common courſe of accurſed Church-robbery.</p>
            <p>Finally, we wiſh that thoſe which obiect ſome divines againſt the divine right of tithes, would for the ſafety of their conſciences, but faithfully obſerve and practiſe thoſe honeſt rules, which the learned men do ſtrictly propound in this point.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:27872:25"/>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>That there muſt be juſt cauſe of ſo doing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>What is alienated muſt bee imployed to ſome good uſe in the Church or Common-wealth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>There muſt be reſerved a ſufficient (not a ſurmiſed) maintenance for an able Miniſtery and reliefe of the poore.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>No good member of the Church, can in conſcience ſeeke the harme and hinderance of the ſame. Then would my text be better obeyed. Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the oxe that treadeth out the corne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>I am to make good the truth of our mentioned doctrin, by diſcourſe of the unequall condition of Impropriations.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Now as the doctrine doth induce this ſubject into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, ſo I intend my following ſpeech hereof at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, onely according to the drift of my doctrine, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, againſt thoſe unjuſt and irreligious Impropriatours, which debarre the labouring Miniſters of the Goſpell, from the meanes of their meet maintenance.</p>
            <p>Tithes (we may collect) continued in ſacred eſteeme and poſſeſſion ſome foure thouſand yeares afore our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviours Incarnation. After his happy birth paſſed alſo about ſix hundred moe, afore the prophane handes of impious ſacriledge durſt invade, and violate theſe Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall rights.</p>
            <p>Then, <hi>horreſco referens,</hi> I tremble to relate it; there happened a diſaſtrous ſeaſon of hatching hatefull mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Behold <hi>Mahomet</hi> acted the falſe Prophet in <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia, Boniface</hi> played the Antichriſt in <hi>Rome, Phocas</hi> moſt cruelly murdered his Maſter <hi>Mauritius</hi> in <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and traytrouſly uſurped the Empire: At which time likewiſe <hi>Carolus Martellus</hi> in the Weſterne parts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of defence, incroached in this kinde upon the Church.</p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding, his faire promiſes (as credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Authours affirm) to reſtore the tithes, &amp;c. lent and entruſted (we are told) unto him, during the <hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:27872:25"/>cruell incurſions, he ſalſifyed his faith, and fruſtrated the Clergies hope, by a wicked and wrongfull aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The old ſaying, <hi>nulla fiaes pietaſque viris qui caſtra ſequuntur,</hi> touch military mens infidelity and propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe appeared abundantly, verified in this martiall and ambitious Prince.</p>
            <p>The city <hi>Tours</hi> upon the <hi>Loyre</hi> continueth a laſting rrophy of his moſt triumphant victory. But his high tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring humour reciprocating with the <hi>Babylonian</hi> beaſt for their own reſpects, &amp; binding his ſoldiets to his aſpiring ſervice with the unlawful nervs of the Church, remaineth a notorious monument of irreligion not of liberalitie.</p>
            <p>The very <hi>Saraſins</hi> whom he ſlew, would have exclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt ſuch evill dealing with their Prieſts. Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry writers of that time, ſuffered him not to eſcape with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſharpe cenſure, yea ſome of them purſue the chace of him untill a fearefull viſion of infernall paines and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments undertooke him, great pitty it was that ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Commander blemiſhed his illuſtrious ſelfe by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch occaſion. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the oxe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was an age when Chriſtian Religion ranne a ſtrong by as of building Monaſteries, and endowing them with large revenues: a firme opinion of the piety and charity or thoſe which were cloyſtered in them procured this ample benevolence.</p>
            <p>Their laudable beginnings in devotion, hoſpitality, and ſundry alme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>deeds were anſwerable. But in proceſſe of time; their idleneſſe bred luxury to undoe their devotion, and their luxury ingendred avarice to deſtroy their charity: and then many whole Benefices ſeemed not ſeldome too few for one Monaſteries de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring ſwallow. Men of no worth ſerved their Churches, and ſpared them wages.</p>
            <p>Theſe men (ſaith one) never of Gods making, but
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:27872:26"/>meere creatures of the Pope, notwithſtanding his Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods protection, and no few opportunities of free cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, did not yet ſo deeply degenerate, but that one of their utter enemies, Maſter <hi>Leaver</hi> in a Sermon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, &amp;c. yeelds them this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
            <p>Whereas fifty tunne bellied Monkes filled their paunches, kept up their houſe, and relieved the whole country round about them: There hath ſucceeded in their place and generation of greedy guttes, devouring the whole houſe, and making great pillage throughout a whole country, yet cannot be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>He mentioneth alſo a world of faire pretenſes of good workes at theſe Monaſteries diſſolution, vaniſhed into nothing but deluſion, and depravation.</p>
            <p>Moreover as at the firſt the Monkes tooke but a ſmall penſion for themſelves, from the appropriate Churches, and left all the reſt to the officiating Vicars; but <hi>reditus tantum ſuperfluos,</hi> a few overplus rents which might well be ſpared ſaith <hi>Panormitan, quando fructus ſunt ſufficientes et abundantes Clerico,</hi> when the other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits are abundantly ſufficient for the Incumbent: <hi>non am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius quam quinquageſimam partem,</hi> no more then the fiftieth part, is a rule in a certaine Councell of <hi>Toledo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So when as they waxed exorbitant and immoderate, their holy Father himſelfe (as they held him) inhibited and confined their inſatiable greedineſſe, as tending to the diſcredit of the Papacy, the ruine of Pariſh Churches, and decay of religion in all places.</p>
            <p>Hereupon Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, commands in <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Worceſter</hi> a reformation, and that the Biſhops ſhould admit none of their preſentation, without a libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall proviſion for the Vicars uſes.</p>
            <p>The contrary he calleth <hi>extirpandae conſuetudinis viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> a wicked cuſtome to be rooted out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clement</hi> the third proceeded further againſt them, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:27872:26"/>in caſe they did not provide and preſent accordingly, he then ordered from them that power to the Ordinarie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth confirmed and inlarged the former decrees. <hi>Clement</hi> the fifth, whetted ſtill a ſharper edge upon the former Conſtitutions, and threatned Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall cenſures upon the perſiſting delinquents.</p>
            <p>Moreover it is knowne, how the Popes (for ſeare of others negligence) had their Apoſtolicall Conſervators in the Vicars behalfes. Neither paſſed any Appropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> without ſpeciall proviſoes for theſe purpoſes, as <hi>Petrus Rebuffus</hi> witneſſeth. And this text was frequently alledged againſt them, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the oxe that treadeth out the corne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may ſoone ſee then by that which hath beene ſaid, how moſt of our moderne Impropriatours come far ſhort of the very Monkes and Popes in piety and honeſt dealing toward the Church.</p>
            <p>That learned man above mentioned, termed theſe ſorts of ſacrilegious abuſes in his time, <hi>perniciem et exitium to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Reipublicae Chriſtianae,</hi> the bane and deſtruction of the whole Chriſtian Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Surely, if hee had lived in this worſer age of ours, and beheld the cunning and cruell multiplication and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of this direfull monſter, he would have fallen into moſt bitter exclamation againſt it, and in ſome manner have reſembled it to the abomination of deſolation ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the holy place where it ought not.</p>
            <p>Alas, it hath waxed apace to the waſte of the Church: It hath quickly augmented into a viperous brood, no leſſe deformed then ravenous, which make no meete conſcience (according to divine command) of the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of our holy mother the Church, and of the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſts Clergy therein, the ſpirituall Paſtours; but take to themſelves the houſes of God in poſſeſſion. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 84. with a helliſh greedineſſe. Neither ſeemed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:27872:27"/>the light of this ſerpentine Monſter any better aſpected then this bodily compoſed ſhape: For certainely if his evill eies had well he held the Sonne of righteouſneſſe, ſuch a gracious influence of ſupernall illumination ſhould the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> have ſhined upon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as they would never thus (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the light of divine religion and naturall reaſon) have inſatiably coveted to muzzle the mouth of the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full oxe, and ſuffer ſome ſlow-bellyed Cretian beaſtes to devour the graine.</p>
            <p>Nor allow the layterers the reward of the labourers: nor ſtarve the induſtrious workeman, and pamper up the idle perſon with his appointed portion.</p>
            <p>The rules amongſt the beſt Lawyers, in this caſe run with a primary reſpect unto the Service of the Churches before any others neceſſities. The Vicar which excriſeth the Cure muſt be preferred above all other perſons, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exempt or not exempted, Religious or Laicke, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall or Secular, Cloyſter and Chapter, &amp;c. be the words of <hi>Bowichius</hi> and <hi>Rebuffus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither do they ſuppoſe a bare ſuſtentation to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient; perchance they write, he ſhall not be driven in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the extremes of want: yet nevertheleſſe the portion may be much incompetent, if we regard a due and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent faſhion (according to the conveniency and dignity of the Miniſteriall calling) in their meate, drinke and clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and other congruencies.</p>
            <p>It is not fit they ſhould be inforced to feed <hi>fabis et ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is vilibus cibariis,</hi> with courſe fare and meane dyet; nor yet their garments to bee of the loweſt ranke: <hi>nec ſibi debent coquere,</hi> neither may they want neceſſary and ſeemely attendance of ſervants. For as that Benefice is incompetent, which doth not well ſuffice to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Incumbent, and thoſe which are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſerve about him.</p>
            <p>So theſe grave and judicious Authours affirme, that whenſoever the Vicars portion commeth in queſtion,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:27872:27"/>
               <hi>conſiderabitur in iis honeſtas, nt honoretur in iis officium ſacerdotale,</hi> the excellency of the Prieſthood with the due requiſites, muſt be worthily conſiderd and honoured, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heu dedecus ingens!</hi> Fie then upon it, when the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriatour boaſteth that hee knoweth how to abound, but the Incumbent is compelled to bewaile that hee knoweth how to be abaſed; when as the Impropriatour laugheth that he knoweth how to be full, but the Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent muſt lament, that hee knoweth how to bee hungry and ſuffer need.</p>
            <p>This is a moſt unequall parting of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> entire ſpeech, <hi>Philippians</hi> fourth, and againſt the tenour of my text.</p>
            <p>It ſavoureth of no good piety nor conſcience, that the Prieſt like <hi>Plinies</hi> fiſh Lutarius, ſhould performe a great deale of labour for food; But the Impropriatour, like the Egyptian fiſh <hi>Sargus,</hi> ſhould ravine up the meat.</p>
            <p>The ſacrilegious would verifie the ſaying of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Canaan Matthew</hi> 15. upon Clergy men; <hi>The Dogs eate of the crummes, which fall from their Maſters table:</hi> And ſo farre as they can, transforme the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry into the Ieſuite <hi>Acoſtaes</hi> poore fiſh <hi>Rambos,</hi> which is faine to ſuſtaine it ſelfe upon thoſe refuſe pittances, that ſlippe out of the devouring mouthes of the inſatiable Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burons.</p>
            <p>It was an old and authenticall plea in the behalfe of the officiating Miniſters for their preeminence, <hi>Vicarius agit de damno vitando, monaſterium vero de lucro captando<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> how the Vicars labour for the good of the ſoule, but the Impropriatours endeavour for the goods of the world.</p>
            <p>What ſigne of equity can then be ſeen in ſo ſtrange and ſiniſter, <hi>ſic vos non vobis;</hi> for the Clergy Bees to do all the buſineſſe in collecting the honey and compoſing the combes, and the Impropriators drones, <hi>ignavium pecus,</hi> to conſume and devour up all the honey, the reward of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:27872:28"/>the others worke?</p>
            <p>For the ſpirituall Shepheards to keepe and to feed the flockes, and nevertheleſſe, the carnall Impropriatours to carry away the fleeces, to reape the profits?</p>
            <p>For theſe birds of the Altar to ſing, and waite upon the Altar, and yet thoſe banes of the Altar to goe away with the benefit of the Altar? For theſe Oxen of the Prieſthood to plow painefully, and yet the prophane Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriatours to muzzle them ſhamefully? <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Emperour <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> hearing how cruelly King <hi>Herod</hi> had dealt with his hopefull children, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that it was better to be one of <hi>Herods</hi> Swine then his Sonne, becauſe Hogges had their priviledge in <hi>Iudea</hi> inviolably preſerved, but <hi>Herods</hi> children were tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſſy murthered, againſt that prerogative which God and nature had given them.</p>
            <p>Thus might we profeſſe in like manner, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Impropriatours oxen ſeemeth much more fairely tollerable, then the ſtate and fortune of their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars and hirelings. Thoſe have commonly their meet &amp; convenient provender to ſtrengthen them unto their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed taſke and buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>But the ordinary portion of theſe is to ſerve &amp; ſterve, to worke and want, to bee earneſt in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, yet without any due reſpect, &amp; reaſon had of them in that deſerving regard.</p>
            <p>We may juſtly complaine at the miſerable indignity of our caſe, with the words of <hi>Bildad, Iob.</hi> 18. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are we counted as beaſts, and reputed vile in your ſight? or rather, why are wee worſe contemned and baſelier reckoned of then bruit creatures?</p>
            <p>Theſe pittileſſe ſorts of oppreſſours reſemble <hi>Pharaoh Necoh,</hi> killing tyrants indeed, to grant theſe Iſraelites no ſufficient ſtraw, and yet to exact the full tale of the bricke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as when they had it; to bereave theſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lampes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:27872:28"/>of their requiſit oyle, and yet to remit nothing of their cantinuall burning:</p>
            <p>To clippe off the helpefull wings of theſe ſacred birdes, and yet to inforce them unto a wonted flight of miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall offices; to cut aſunder the uſefull ſinewes of theſe men of God, and yet to call upon them to runne the race that is ſet before them: to diſarme theſe Soldiours of Chriſt from their neceſſary proviſion and weapons, and yet <hi>in praelia trudere inermes,</hi> to urge them into warfare, and thruſt them upon the front of the battell.</p>
            <p>To deny fit tooles and meet materials, and yet to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine theſe myſticall Architects for to toyle and build, as if they had abundance: to ſuppreſſe the meanes of all decent performance, and yet to preſſe the practice of all manner of duties; whith holdes no good quarter with the rule of my text: <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon a ſtrange ſurfit which ſome ill tempered Clergy men, once tooke by a ſodaine overflow of outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, after a long time of perſecution, aroſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb of the Churches daughter riches which undid her Mother.</p>
            <p>Here was need to reforme the diſorderly and peccant members, but not to remove the divinely appropriate meanes, to apply a remedy, not to oppoſe a ruine.</p>
            <p>What an unconſcionable and cruell inequality is then diſcernable in the Impropriatours courſe, which by one ravenous mouth of ſacriledge, do devour both mother &amp; daughter; ſpoyling Chriſt and ſwallowing up his Spouſe; robbing the Lord, and ruinating the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer?</p>
            <p>What cares the Atheiſt for honeſt payment of his tithes, when as he hath deſpiſed all true religion? What faithfulneſſe may wee find in the Papiſts touching this point of tenths, ſince that he diſtaſteth our preſent reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion?</p>
            <p>But the Proteſtant Impropriattour ſeemeth to ſurpaſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:27872:29"/>them both in exceſſe of Church robbery: For he teacheth that a man ſhould not ſteale, and yet himſelfe ſtealeth, he abhorreth idols, and yet he committeth ſacriledge: hee ſaith a man ſhould avoid adultery, and yet he runneth a whoring after his owne inventions: he maketh his, boaſt of the Law, and yet thorow breaking of the Law hee diſhonoureth God, and cauſeth his Name to be blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med among the Gentiles, <hi>Romans</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Will a man rob God? yet they have robbed him in his tithes and offerings, and ſo are curſed with a curſe: <hi>Malachi.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>This was at the ſiege of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> one of <hi>Ioſephus</hi> grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous expoſtulations againſt <hi>Iohn</hi> and others of the ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; if any man ſhould take from thee thy daily food, no doubt, but thou wouldeſt account him thine enemy: canſt thou then hope that God, whom thou haſt depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of daily Sacrifice, will aſſiſt thee?</p>
            <p>Theſe Impropriatours, which debarre the labouring Miniſters of the word, from their liberall maintenance, deale no better with the Lord touching his worſhip and Service; what favour then can they flatter themſelves with to finde at his hand, without heartie repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance?</p>
            <p>Time and cuſtome with ſome colour of authority have taken away the ſenſe of this ſinne, and turned the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſeleſſe offenders into the braſen faced impudency of <hi>Solomons</hi> harlot, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 30. <hi>Such is the way of an adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Woman, ſhe eateth and wipeth her mouth, and ſaith, I have done no wickedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some ſerpentine Patrons of theſe uſurpers upon the Clergies patrimonie are content to permit (where they cannot prohibite) a continuation of tithes ſtill to the Minniſtery, <hi>per vim exemplarem,</hi> by imitation of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſh ſtate ordered by the Almighty; but not <hi>per vim oblig ativam,</hi> by any binding force under the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Our divine right to the tithes is already (in a ſtipulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:27872:29"/>to our propounded doctrine) manifoldly made good. But admit we had (as they ſaine and ſuggeſt) no obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory warrant, but onely an exemplary vertue to plead for our intereſts, yet this ſeemes enough to ſhoote ſuch Iulianizers through with their owne ſhaftes.</p>
            <p>For where can the Impropriatours ſhew ſo much co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to countenance their ſecrilegious incroachments?</p>
            <p>Did ever the Indiciall Lawes of the <hi>Iewes</hi> afford them any ſuch exemplary matter, to maintaine their caſe with? No ſurely, for Nature, Law, Goſpell, <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile, Grecian</hi> and <hi>Barbarian</hi> have often given the voyces of their practiſes and proteſtations, againſt all ſuch invaders of the Prieſts inheritance.</p>
            <p>And yet, (tell it not in <hi>Gath,</hi> neither publiſh it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the wall of <hi>Aſkelon,</hi> let not the uncircumciſed know of it) there are many perſons named Chriſtians, who to mount up themſelves into the higheſt roomes of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Magnificoes, make no conſcience to diminiſh and caſt downe the Miniſters of the word, into the loweſt cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of miſerable mendicants.</p>
            <p>No ſmall ſcandall to our Religion is this contumacy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the divine Injunction, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> affirmeth <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. <hi>that the ſtrong ought to beare the infirmities of the weake,</hi> this is a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rule concerning all ſorts.</p>
            <p>But the Impropriatour(whoſe brow is braſſe, whoſe necke is an iron ſinew, and whoſe heart is as hard as flint) he regardeth it with the leaſt, although it bindeth him with the moſt. He rampeth like a ſtrong Lion upon the prey of the benefit, but he leaveth the whole burden to oppreſſe the weake Incumbent.</p>
            <p>Wee are told <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> 22. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſee thy brothers aſſe, or his oxe fall down by the way, and hide thy ſelf from them; thou ſhalt ſurely help him to lift them up again; yea, be they the beaſts of him that hateth thee. Exo.</hi> 23</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:27872:30"/>
            <p>But alas, there are too many Savage beaſts in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces beſides <hi>Epheſus.</hi> 1 <hi>Corinthians.</hi> 15. Namely cruell and bruitiſh men (<hi>Theophylact</hi> and <hi>Primaſius</hi> interpret the words) which practiſe nothing more then to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe downe the painfull <hi>Pauls</hi> of the Clergy, and to let them lie in all extremity.</p>
            <p>We read 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. <hi>Who ſo hath this worlds good, and ſeeth his brother need and ſhutteth up his bowels of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion from him, how dwelleth the love of GOD in him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, whiles theſe impious <hi>Belſhazzars</hi> may drink and quaffe with their companions in the golden &amp; ſilver veſſels taken out of the houſe of God <hi>Daniel.</hi> 5. whiles this mercileſſe brood, may with the rich glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, be cloathed in purple and ſine linen, and fare ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly every day. <hi>Luke.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>They have ſmall compaſſion at the <hi>Lazarus</hi> of the spoyled Miniſtery, which want not ſeldome, the refuſe, that fall from their rich Tables: yet they have ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe at the <hi>Lazarus</hi> of many famiſhing ſoules; ſterved through the accurſed meanes of their execrable ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>They have ſmall reſpect at the grievous conſequences of their corrupt example, becauſe upon the opening of this bottomeleſſe pit, a groſſe and diſmall ſmoke ariſeth, by reaſon of which the Sunne and the aire are darkened. <hi>Apocalypſe.</hi> 9. <hi>fugêrê pudor, verumque, fideſque; in quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſubîere locum fraudeſque dolique, infidiaeque, et vis, et amor ſceleratus habendi:</hi> All true devotion and pious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the Church conſumed away; and there preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into their place all manner of covetous circumventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſacrilegious rapine. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzlee the mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold from hence alſo a ſwerving world of leſſer Church theeves tooke heart afreſh to commit manifold ſpoyle upon the Clergy. They excuſe themſelves by the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:27872:30"/>Impropriators ravening up totall Benefices, to purloine &amp; invade ſmaller parcels of tithes and glebes.</p>
            <p>Like the Pirate, who juſtified his robbing of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Sea-faring paſſengers, with a few Gallies; becauſe <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, with huge Armies and Navies pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laged &amp; preyed upon whole Kingdomes and Provinces.</p>
            <p>No mervaile then that this Impropriation Monſter, meeteth with ſo bad mention not onely among grave Divines, but alſo great Lawyers.</p>
            <p>The Lord chiefe Iuſtice <hi>Cooke,</hi> that late was, obſerved out of Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory, how <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata having a purpoſe wholly to ruine the profeſſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, from which himſelfe had fouly revolted; uſed not the ſword (as other perſecutors did) but tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the meanes of the Miniſtery, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This crafty Fox well knew that the depriving them of theſe, would neceſſarily draw on the deſtruction of the other. And thus diveliſh is the prophane Impropriatours dealing.</p>
            <p>He uttereth at laſt this propheticall ſentence, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of the revenues of the holy Church, will one day bee the ſubverſion of the Service of God, and of his Religion.</p>
            <p>Learned <hi>Plowden</hi> in his Commentaries writeth of this obſervation long ſince by our reverend Iudges, how the Monkes perfidious purloining all the chiefe profits to themſelves, from the poore Vicars, uſhered in a world of wicked abuſes. And this is the prophane Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriatours impious caſe.</p>
            <p>He addeth, as the revenue of the Pariſh Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed, ſo likewiſe did preaching. The Emperour <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> was wont to affirme, that from the beggery of the Miniſtery, followes the ſubverſion of that holy order, and conſequently of true Religion. But herein the notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Impropriators muſt be appealed as grievouſly guilty.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſacred horſe-leaches which never are ſatiated, <hi>Prover.</hi> 30. they have little regard to the fearefull judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:27872:31"/>of God, who, at length without repentance and reſtitution, will verifie upon them <hi>Solomans</hi> divinely inſpired ſaying; <hi>It is a ſnare to the man who devoureth that which is holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The King will queſtion how they came in hither, not having a wedding garment? And bids his ſervantes bind them hand and foote, and take them away, and caſt them into utter darkeneſſe, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> Matthew. 22. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the oxe that treadeth out the corne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. We demonſtrate our obſervation from the reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of ſundry inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>veniences which are incurred through defect of its due execution; when as the painfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are deprived of their competent maintenance.</p>
            <p n="1">1 We ſet down the decay of true Religion. Doctor <hi>Andrews</hi> a Prelate of famous memory, diſcovereth an indiſſolvable combination between ſacred manners, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred meanes, ſacred perſons, and ſacred revenues.</p>
            <p>Theſe he accounteth ſo cloſely connexed, as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring of the one is the violation of them all. And whiles the Laitie would ſwallow the laſt, they ſubvert the reſt.</p>
            <p>It may be granted indeed to come for the moſt part to paſſe, that when the portions of the Levites are not given them, they flee every one to his field, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 13. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, in their abſence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where is the teaching Prieſt? but the wants of him bringeth men to be without the true God, and witbout Law, 2. <hi>Chron</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Romans</hi> 10. <hi>How ſhall they call on him in whom they have not believed? and how ſhall they beleeve in him of whom they have not heard? and how ſhall they heare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Preacher? and how ſhall they preach except they be ſent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how may we preſume that the Lord will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe to ſend them which bring glad tydings of good things, and preach the Goſpell of peace, unleſſe men
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:27872:31"/>thought their feet more beautifull, and gave them better welcome.</p>
            <p>But verily if this indignation happen, then <hi>Proverbs</hi> 29 <hi>There is no viſion, then the people muſt needs periſh. For behold then the days come, ſaith the Lord God, that I will ſend a famine into the Land, not a famine of bread, uor a thirſt for water, but of hearing the Word of the Lord. And they ſhall wander from Sea to Sea, and from the North even to the Eaſt; they ſhall run too and fro to ſeeke the Word of the Lord, and ſhall not finde it,</hi> Amos 8.</p>
            <p>Monſtrous then is the miſchiefe and miſery of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable and direfull voracitie of ſacred revenues, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of ſacred perſons, of ſacred manners, of ſacred means: And in the execrable ravine of them, loe, theſe myſticall Canibals ſwallow up alſo humane creatures ſouls.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Quis talia faendo Myrmidonum,</l>
               <l>Dolopumve, aut duri miles <hi>Vlyſſi,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Temperet a lachrymis?—</l>
            </q>
            <p>What ſtony hearted perſon would not diſtill down ſhowres of teares at ſuch a ſpirituall deſtruction? <hi>Have all the workers of iniquity no knowledge, who eat up my people as they eat bread, and call not upon the Lord? Pſ.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>Honour is the nurſe of good Arts; Preferment is the promoter of Vertues: a liberall ſtipend allureth the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Souldiers unto ſervice: good wages attract the greateſt labourers beſt diligence: the richneſſe of the prize addeth winged ſpeed unto the runners of a race; the ſufficient furniture of the rack &amp; manger doth ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the work of the toylſome oxen: the plants of the Sanctuary will not well proſper, without the waters of the Sanctuary ſupple and refreſh them: <hi>Ezech.</hi> 47.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> commanded the people that dwelt in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to give the portion of the Prieſts and the Levites, that they might be incouraged in the Law of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> told the <hi>Athenians</hi> how they muſt not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:27872:32"/>expect to finde ſuch men, who to do them ſervice, would be willing to undo their own ſelves.</p>
            <p>Neither is it to be thought, that men of excellent parts and eminent hopes can be readily wonne unto this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine profeſſion (Maſter <hi>Perkins</hi> complayneth) whiles the ſacred Miniſtery is ſo frequently compelled to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme a laborious travaile in the ſhamefull and tedious path way of beggery, and much contempt over-dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Clergie.</p>
            <p>God in his Law (he further ſheweth) took a ſtrict or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to prevent this miſchiefe touching the livings of the Levits. If he had not ſo ordained, it is like the corruption of men might have driven them to no leſſe extremities, then are the Miniſters of this age, who now (under the Goſpell) be left much unprovided, although deſerving to be beſt rewarded.</p>
            <p>He commendeth the children of this world (meaning the Papiſts) as much wiſer in their kinde concerning this point, then the Church of God, which he affirmeth to be a notorious blemiſh unto the reformed profeſſion, likewiſe a lamentable eclypſe unto the beauty &amp; bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Religion.</p>
            <p>Leſt therfore the number of able Paſtors ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe apace, and the knowledge of the Goſpell among us decay with them as faſt: hee doth earneſtly wiſh and admoniſh both Supetiours and Inferiours to be carefull and jealous in their ſeverall places for providing a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient remedy againſt this dangerous inconvenience.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Panormitan</hi> well obſerveth, <hi>Adtennitatem Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiorum neceſſariò ſequitur ignorantia ſacerdotum:</hi> An unlearned and diſable Miniſtery is for the moſt part oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned from the poorneſſe of Eccleſiaſticall Livings.</p>
            <p>And Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third blaming the horrible avarice and abuſe of many Impropriating Monks, addeth this as the curſed fruit of ſo vile and impious a practice, That in thoſe Regions ſcarce could there be found any
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:27872:32"/>Parochiall Prieſt, who had even ſo much as a ſmall porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of skill in the liberall Arts. From whence (Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the Third truly declared) <hi>pericula imminent ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum,</hi> the grievous dangers of humane creatures ſouls do grow on apace.</p>
            <p>If men held in as deer a regard their immortall ſouls, as they generally do their corruptible bodies, then would they never thus baſely grudge unto the Paſtors of them a liberall affluence of all neceſſaries: ſo that no want of worthy reſpect, nor of time, nor of means, might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them from making meet and manifold proviſion to lead, to feed, to fold to defend their flocks.</p>
            <p>But wheras the needfull ſprings of theſe due ſupplyes become dry or diverted, Behold there the very life of the Miniſters duty, and the peoples edification langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth.</p>
            <p>The ſheep will range and ſcatter up and down at their own pleaſures: <hi>Sordent quae poſſunt ſemper haberi,</hi> All their longing is for ſtrange Novelties, with unworthy neglect of their own Paſtors, and ſo through their ſides they wound Religion.</p>
            <p>The Shepheard (whoſe living is little better then an Almes) is over-much loden with the ſtudy of looking for himſelf and his family, he cannot care as hee ought, for his Cure. Hereupon his owne preſſures and exigences confine the precious liberty of his place into obſequious ſlavery.</p>
            <p>Thus whiles they fear to be thought enemies for tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the truth, they fall by flattery to trade for untruſty friends: they act the fawning Paraſites in ſtead of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Preachers: &amp; not daring to profeſſe themſelves honeſt Freemen of <hi>Verona,</hi> they appear the ſervile vaſſals of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and <hi>Placentia:</hi> becauſe compoſed to praiſe and pleaſe, but not to reprove and pierce.</p>
            <p>The ſword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. they bear in vain, for they have no courage to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:27872:33"/>cry aloud, not to ſpare, to lift up their voices like trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, and to ſhew the people their tranſgreſſions, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> 58.</p>
            <p>Neceſſitie inſinuates a ſafer ſeeming courſe, namely, to ſooth up their ſins, whoſe benevolence they always need, and whoſe evill will they are not able to undergo. Thus they proclayme peace, and there was no peace: and one built up a wall, and ſo others dawbed it with untempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mortar, and ſow pillows to all arm-holes, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 13. to the diſhonour of God, to the ruine of Religion, to the deſtruction of ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hinc prima mali labes:</hi> this peſtilent miſchief ſprung from the impious neglect of this precept: <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I alledge two profane derogation from God, firſt in his honour; Becauſe, when as 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>We are Ambaſſadors for Chriſt,</hi> it followeth then according to our Saviours ſaying, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. <hi>He that heareth you heareth me, and hee that deſpiſeth you, despiſeth me, and hee that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſeut me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Earthly Princes (in reſpect of themſelves intereſſed) be never wont to diſpenſe with wrong and diſgraces done their Meſſengers, but expect in all places their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy entertainment: witneſſe <hi>David's</hi> revenge upon <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nun</hi> the King of the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> for this abuſe: Alſo for the like offence, the utter ſubverſion of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous City <hi>Corinth</hi> by the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely the Almighty Lord muſt bee imagined much more ſenſible of contempt and injuries offered againſt thoſe whom he ſendeth, in regard of his ſupreme Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty intereſted with his delegated ſervants.</p>
            <p>Behold in his ſpeech unto the Prophet <hi>Samuel,</hi> What he ſaith unto all his Miniſters; <hi>they have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me.</hi> He that honoureth the Prieſt, honnoureth God, and he that deſpiſeth the Prieſt, by little and little falleth to this alſo, that he will uſe reproach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:27872:33"/>God himſelf, Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> ſheweth.</p>
            <p>But how ſhould this requiſite honour be duly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med without his meet and appointed Miniſters. Again, how ſhould thoſe Miniſters of his ſufficiently attend their Function without anſwerable mayntenance? But ſacriledge deſpoyling them of that, doth conſequently derogate from God in his honour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It derogateth from God in his rightfull clayme and intereſt. <hi>The earth it the Lords, and the fulneſſe therof, the world and they that dwell therin,</hi> Pſal. 24. <hi>Conſideret homo quod omnia Dei ſunt per quae vivit, ſine terra, ſine flumina, ſine ſemina:</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> adviſeth man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that all the means of his life come from God. Yea, he induceth his Majeſty thus expoſtulating this caſe; <hi>Meus eſt homo quem feci; mea eſt terra quam collis; mea ſunt ſemina quae ſpargis: mea animalia quae fatigas: mei ſunt imbres &amp; pluviae: &amp; ventorum flamina mea ſunt: meus eſt Solis calor: omnia vivendi alimenta mea, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mine is the Man whom I have made; mine is the Land which the labourer tilleth; mine are the ſeeds which the Husbandmen ſow: mine are the beaſts which be toyled and wearied in the work: mine are the ſoaking ſhowres and refreſhfull rains: the cheriſhing windes receive alſo from me their welcome wings; the comfortable heat of the Sun is mine; I am likewiſe the Lord of all the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wherby thou liveſt.</p>
            <p>Since then God is the ſupreme owner of all, and from his free bounty flows our totall maintenance, the duty of juſtice and gratitude bindeth us to render ſomething back for a token of his Soveraignty, and a teſtimony of our thanks.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> writeth, that it was the uſe of the Church through the World in his time, and received from the Apoſtles; to offer ſome things of the bleſſings that they lived by, as the firſt-fruits therof to him, who gave theſe things unto them.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:27872:34"/>
            <p>Now <hi>qui dignatus eſt totum dare, decimaem à nobis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnatur repetere,</hi> God that vouchſafed to give us the whole, vouchſafeth alſo to require back again the tenth. This moſt munificent beſtower of all the reſt, reſerveth only but that part unto himſelfe (for that his holy Word proclaymeth to be his inheritance, ſeparate to his ſervice) and a portion out of the other nine parts to relieve and ſupply the poor.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever therfore (ſaith the ſame <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous either to gain unto himſelf a gracious reward; or to intreat an indulgent remiſſion of his ſins; let him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionably pay the tenth to the Clergy, and out of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue parts, let him charitably compaſſionate the poor.</p>
            <p>Oh mankinde (hee further addeth) empty of zealous devotion, but full of perfidious defraudation, ſince thou canſt not but know, that all good things which thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeſt are the Lords, what an unthankfull heart then haſt thou oh unworthy wretch, to return nothing back again of his own to the giver of all things demanding it? Lo what hee requireth is a due debt and tribute: thou canſt not deny it, thou muſt not diminiſh it, thou mayſt not delay it, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This ſacrilegious uſurpation of the Miniſters main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance doth derogate from God in his wiſdome: There are many learned perſons (and ſome of their opinions ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in print) although not ſo reſolutely holding tithes to be due by divine right, yet they conceive no courſe elſe ſo apt and indifferent for the Clergies proviſion as by the payment of them.</p>
            <p>And this the reaſon which they alledge herein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe every politike Law is to be ſuppoſed the more right and equall, by how much it reſembleth and approcheth neerer to the Law of the ſame kinde, which the Lord hath ordained amongſt the <hi>Hebrews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is certain that the Law of God among the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> was for the payment of tithes unto the Miſters
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:27872:34"/>which officiated in holy duties, as well in one place of that Countrey as in another: and therefore the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of them ſtill to the ſame purpoſe ſeemeth very requiſite.</p>
            <p>Moreover, it is a common maxime, <hi>Vetus lex nulla an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquanda eſt, quae neque imbecillis ſit, neqne inutilis;</hi> no old Law is to be abrogated, which neither is too weak nor unprofitable.</p>
            <p>When as therfore no want of worth, no waſte of ſtrength, no wane of utility can be diſcovered in this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely enacted Statute touching tithes for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Gualter</hi> on <hi>Matthew</hi> 23, ſaith, <hi>Quae juſtior ratio excogitari poteſt alendi miniſtros, quàm ut ex decimis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant?</hi> What juſter courſe can be deviſed? what better reaſon may be imagined for the Clergies maintenance, then to receive the meanes hereof by the payment of tithes?</p>
            <p>Surely then it ſavoureth of no good diſcretion nor conſcience in man (as if he preſumed himſelf wiſer than his Maker) to diſanull this Law. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. I urge that the withholding competent mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from the labouring Miniſters is contrary unto le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall right in ſundry reſpects.</p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Rives</hi> obſerveth that both the ancient grants of Appropriations, and the formes of confirming them from <hi>Rome</hi> run in this manner; ſaving the ſuſtentation of the Vicar, and the right of the Biſhop; reſerving to us and our ſucceſſors free power, when as it behoveth, of ſupplying and augmenting the Vicars portion, out of the tithes, &amp;c. for his better undergoing the burthen of his Cure, and charges payable therout,</p>
            <p>Yea, he inferreth out <hi>Ludovieus Romanus,</hi> that the Solution of procurations was <hi>pro modo facultatum Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae,</hi> as the Church hath ability to ſpare them. For thus is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:27872:35"/>the minde and words of the Law ſaith <hi>Hoſtienſis, ut Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia ultra poſſe non gravetur,</hi> the viſitor muſt beare his owne charges, rather then bee grievous unto the Church.</p>
            <p>Moreover how the Lawes of the Land conſent here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with in favour of the diſtreſſed Vicar, he alledgeth ſome Statutes in the reigne of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, that the Dioceſan of the place, in the conceſſion of any Appropriation ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly and piouſly ordaine a yeerely ſumme of money for reliefe of the poore, and the Vicar to be well and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently endowed.</p>
            <p>At length he profeſſeth, that he could never know of any Statute, made ſince the Abbey-diſſolution either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogative or derogatory, to the Common Lawes in his caſe.</p>
            <p>And when as thoſe monaſticall houſes, &amp;c. were put downe, the King and his heires for ever were by the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute to hold them, in the ſame ample manner as the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot then had in the right of his place: And ſaving to all perſons, Bodies politique and their Succeſſours, all ſuch right, claime, title, intereſt, poſſeſſion, rent-charges, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuities, Leaſes, Farmes, Offices, Fees, Portions, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frons, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe words ſeeme of much efficacy and extent. I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre from them; a Vicar had at the time of diſſolution, right, claime, and intereſt to ſo much of the Appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Rectory as was requiſite for his congruous, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent maintenance: this right is therefore ſtill reſerved to him and his Succeſſours.</p>
            <p>Had the Monaſteries continued, this action bad beene good againſt them: and that they well knew, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſought to fortifie themſelves againſt it, by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbents oath, bond, and by purchaſe of the Popes pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge.</p>
            <p>So now they being diſſolved, the action holds ſtill good
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:27872:36"/>againſt the Impropriatours ſucceeding in the Abbots place.</p>
            <p>The Dioceſan likewiſe at that ſeaſon, had a right of power, and Iuriſdiction in himſelfe, whenſoever the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot preſented a Clerke unto him for inſtitution, not to admit him without a convenient portion, aſſigned for his maintenance. Which if the Abbot performed not within the time limited, then had the Biſhop right in himſelfe to collate the Vicaridge, and to make a fit al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance at his diſcretion, out of the ſequeſtred fruits and profits of the Appropriation.</p>
            <p>And in caſe of relectancy and diſobedience, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſan, might compell the Abbot by Eccleſiaſticall cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, &amp; if he ſtood refractory, there followed impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the ſecular power, without-baile or mainprize, untill the order were obeyed.</p>
            <p>And if hee preſented not at all, the Biſhop then had that right devolved unto him as in caſe of lapſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this right remaineth ſafe unto the Dioceſans ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Impropriatours: And they indeed, as with no good conſcience; ſo againſt juſt law incroach, and uſurpe upon all theſe rights. Moreover, it ſavoureth of a diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition both une quall, and unmercifull in theſe Impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atours, to oppoſe a new augmentation of Vicaridge en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments; becauſe (beſides of many damnable cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers defalcations) the rates of all things are now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunſed unto higher prices: in which reſpect, day la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers arc allowed by Law to raiſe their wages: Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, although King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight diſſolved the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries, yet hee continued that Religion ſtill, that brought the Vicars (beyond their portion) a great part of their maintenance, in oblations, altarages, confeſſion, profits, Maſſe-moneys, and ſuch like Fees.</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore that now a pious reformation, hath put theſe out of date and uſe, juſt reaſon and equity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a ſupply, and recompence to the Vicars in lieu of them.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:27872:38"/>
            <p>Finally, ſince tithes were given in conſideration of preaching the word, and miniſtring the Sacraments, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the payers of them: <hi>Beneficium non debetur niſi prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter officium,</hi> ſpirituall benefices &amp; ſpirituall offices ſhould be relatives.</p>
            <p>What Iuſtice then appeareth, for the people to be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for to pay unto the Improptiatours, the tenth which never doe Miniſter unto them, in the ſacred exerciſes of the Service of God; And thoſe of that divine function which performe theſe parts towards them, are put off with ſo poore and baſe a parcell; as that learned and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Civilian-Docter <hi>Rives</hi> hath in regard thereof, this written wiſh;
<q>
                  <l>Our horſe-boyes wages are not great,</l>
                  <l>Would God our Vicars ware no worſe.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Woe unto him that coveteth an evill covetouſneſſe to his houſe, that hee may ſet his neſt on high: he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted ſhame to his houſe, and finned againſt his ſoule. <hi>For the ſtone ſhall cry out of the wall, and the beame out of the timber ſhall anſwere it, Habakkuk.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Let the perverſe uſurpers of tithes, glebes, &amp;c. pleaſe their fancies and prevaricate with others, under a miſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terme of their turning into Chattels and Lay-fees. If they had quite loſt (through their forced alienation) the quality and nature of Church duties and goods, why were the prophane intruders upon them faine to be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by favour of a Statute in the three and thirtieth of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, to ſue for them in Eccleſiaſticall Courts, and not have recovered them at the Common Law?</p>
            <p>Surely then they ceaſe not their continuall cries againſt the unrighteous detainers of them, with the ſtone in the wall, with the beame out of the rafter, and with the hedge unto the field; this is not our place, let us returne, &amp;c. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:27872:35"/>
            <p n="4">4. I object farther, this prophane defrauding of the Miniſters in their maintenance, appeareth wilfully to ſhut the eyes againſt the light of naturall reaſon, which ſhineth forth with the luſter of this concluſion, that the workeman ought in equity to have his wages, and the labourers deſerve to receive their reward.</p>
            <p>This ſeemeth a character ſo deeply ingraven in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reaſon, as although the direfull hands of impious ſacriledge, be ſhamefully audacious to incroach upon the ſubſtance of the tithes, &amp;c. yet are they not ſufficiently able to extinguiſh the ſtampes of it's truth.</p>
            <p>Namely, that the excellency of the Clergies labour (being in quality and induſtry, in place and paines ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereminent above others muſt needs aptly challenge the moſt worthy ſtipend and beſt temuneration.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe the Lord Archbiſhop <hi>Sandes,</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that there is no ſtate (though of that heigth, as feare, honour, obedience and tribute is due to it) which may more rightly challenge a competent and ſufficient living, then the Miniſters of the word of God.</p>
            <p>Wherfore thoſe which repine at the reaſonable maintenance of them, they ſeeme to have put out the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry light of nature in themſelves.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Becauſe this hinderance and detraction of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Paſtours portion is very averſe, and degenerate from the conceit and courſe of venerable Antiquity.</p>
            <p>For <hi>decimae erant ante legem ſub conſilis; in lege ſub praecepto, poſt legem in libertate Spiritus,</hi> the payment of tenths, before the Law ſeemed to ſubſiſt under counſell, and in the time thereof they ſtood firme by precept, and when as that was once expired, ſtill they are good in the Evangelicall liberty of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>As in the ſeaſon of the old Law, the affection of the faithfull people unto the Temple and Service there ſpared no expences: yea, ſome of the chiefeſt Princes of the <hi>Gentiles, Cyrus, Artaxerxes, Darins, Alexander Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:27872:36"/>Ptolomeus Philadelphus, Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> &amp;c. ſhewed themſelves in this ſort exceedingly bounteous.</p>
            <p>So ſince the birth of our Saviour Chriſt, the pious mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence of Emperours, Kings, &amp;c. alſo the jealous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of Chriſtian people ran in the current of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall addition to the Churches patrimony, but not in ſubſtraction from her propriety.</p>
            <p>The Clergy held their Lands free from Taxes and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, their children held their Inheritance with like freedome in honour of their Fathers Prieſt-hood.</p>
            <p>But now a long time, ſince helliſh iniquity hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded, the holy love of the moſt part of our Chriſtian World is waxed cold: the dolefull tune of the deſolate Churches Song is thus ſad and lamentable, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 24. <hi>My leanneſſe, my leanneſſe, wo unto me: the treacherous dealers have dealt treacherouſly; yea, the treacherous dealers have dealt very treacherouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> of excellent memory imployed in ſome places of his Realmes, pious wiſdome and power for a relief of our Sions ſhamefull diſtreſſe. Hee gave more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over many thouſand Acres of good ground to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Churches, an illuſtrious monument of his religious libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality.</p>
            <p>Our now moſt gracious King (God be thanked) fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the devout foot-ſteps of his happy Father in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall protection and favour of his Clergy. His Majeſties Sovereigne power and ſanctified diſpoſition is able and willing with the precious balme of heavenly juſtice, to cure this otherwiſe unrecoverable and inveterate ulcer, and to compell the due practice of this divine precept: <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the month, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. I alledge when the maintenance of the Miniſters lyeth at ſuch a low ebbe, it uſually occaſioneth Schiſme in the Church, and Faction of the State; eſpecially (as for the moſt part commeth to paſſe) where poore beneficed Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes are moſt populous.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:27872:37"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:27872:37"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:27872:38"/>
            <p>Amongſt ſundry wiſe and learned perſons ſacriledge hath been concluded the prophane mother of theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed daughters.</p>
            <p>It is no leſſe lamentable then ſhameful to conſider ſome Clergy men (through defect of a legall proviſion) being ſtung with the, ſmart of want, and put to extremity, they are forc'd to ſubmit their necks unto a ſlaviſh yoke of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile dependance, and baſe engagement unto their weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier people, who are able to ſuccour and ſupport them.</p>
            <p>They are bound to the baſe peace of obſequious flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by the cruell chaine of intolerable neceſſitie: ſo they dare not but quietly digeſt, whatſoever theſe inordinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do, either in converſation of life, or by confuſion at Church, either in the rudeneſſe of their works, or by the irregularity of their worſhip.</p>
            <p>Neither durſt they refuſe to ſtand as they ſet them, for ſingle Cyphers, and ſuffer them patiently to number their ſummes (at their own pleaſures) with the figures of ſuch idolized Miniſters as they moſt fancy, whether <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Apollo,</hi> or <hi>Cephas:</hi> yea, I wiſh there wanted cauſe ſometimes to adde, be he <hi>Martin Mar-prelate,</hi> or <hi>Julian,</hi> or <hi>Iudas,</hi> or Satan transforming himſelfe into an Angell of light, they may ſcarce murmure at his prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Moreover, whiles the Clergy remayneth miſerably oppreſſed with poverty (which contempt of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and neglect of their Miniſtery uſually accompany) ſo long doth that neceſſity of theirs, being of an active nature, ſeeme to call in many of them a continuall ſcruti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of deviſes and ſhifts for the ſuccour and reliefe of it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And becauſe thoſe courſes which ſwimme againſt the common ſtream of goverment, and nevertheleſſe carry an externall countenance of piety and ſincerity, have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver appeared moſt prevalent for the promotion of ſiniſter
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:27872:39"/>deſignes; they palliate their ſubtile practice under this ſpecious habit.</p>
            <p>Thus they declaim againſt the corruption of the times, and bitterly inveigh againſt the Ceremonies and Polity of the Church.</p>
            <p>It is their uſuall property to ſpeak evill of thoſe which are in Authority: chiefly they draw our the ſharp ſword of Schiſmaticall cenſure againſt Eccleſiaſticall Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours.</p>
            <p>The drift of their whole doctrine concerning them ſoundeth always With this Anabaptiſticall accent, down with them to the ground.</p>
            <p>They never preach againſt Church-robbery, nor preſſe in any Sermon the true payment of tithes. But for their own peculiar intereſts (without any due diſtinguiſhment of different reaſons) they perſwade this Paradoxe, how when the Church is pooreſt, ſhe is pureſt.</p>
            <p>And wheras the ancient Fathers determined out of the ſacred Scriptures, that God is to be worſhiped with ſome liberall return of his own bounty. And how hee muſt be thankfully acknowledged for the munificent Lord and Donor of all bleſſings, by a devout and free-hearted reflux, and rendring back again a meet and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient portion of the good things and benefits given us, to his honour and ſervice.</p>
            <p>Such ſentences they inſimulate to favour of Popiſh ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and whiles they are ſure God hath no neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they are as ſecure to do him no dutie: condemning for an errour in opinion to offer unto him, but commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as a mayn ingredient of Reformation to take away from his Church.</p>
            <p>Thus having by theſe plauſible inſinuations skrewed themſelves into a world of the peoples affections, unto whom nothing for the moſt part, is wont to be more gratefull and pleaſing, then liberty of cenſure, matter of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:27872:39"/>innovation, diſorder, ſingularity, and Religion at their owne price (which is next coſt nothing) lo, They get private gains out of the publike loſſes; &amp; having brought conformable Miniſters out of a good conceit into an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill eſtimation with their Pariſhes, they climbe up by their breaches, and ſupply themſelves with benevolences ariſing out of t he others ruines.</p>
            <p>Theſe crooked practices have already had their dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequences: the world hath ſeldome been with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out many bleeding witneſſes hereof. <hi>Germany</hi> in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular may be wayle not onely her flain thouſands with <hi>Saul,</hi> nor ten thouſands with <hi>David,</hi> but her handred thouſands.</p>
            <p>For Schiſme is not accuſtomed to ſtay long confined in the Church, but ſhee is likewiſe wont to diſſeminate Faction in the State.</p>
            <p>Archbiſhop <hi>Sands</hi> (of excellent memory for the cauſe of the Goſpel) preached at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe, that by reaſon of the want of worthy wages unto theſe workmen for ſalvation, this miſchief ſpreadeth wider, and regardeth as little the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> as the Chaire of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Scepter as the Book, the Prince a the Prophet, the Civill a the Eccleſiaſticall State.</p>
            <p>Thus as unity and peace between the Soveraigne and the Subjects, and withall the people mutually among themſelves, comprehends the true and proper glory of earthly Kingdomes, typically figuring the celeſtiall unity in bleſſedneſſe and eminency of the Triumphant Church of God.</p>
            <p>So Schiſme and Diviſion of any people into variety of opinions and affections, is the bane and ſubverſion of a Church and Nation, reſembling the confuſions and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations of Satans infernall Regiment.</p>
            <p>But theſe will never be totally ſuppreſſed, nor can there want wicked inſtruments to incourage the Subjects for
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:27872:40"/>to run a courſe of contrariety and oppoſition to the laws and perſonall practice of the Prince himſelfe, in matters converſant about the exerciſe of Religion.</p>
            <p>Neither ſhall we be free from the hazard of perillous Faction in our State by occaſion hereof, untill the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of a proportionable mayntenance for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Paſtors doth arme and animate them by example and doctrine to teach and practice (without puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous dread or dependance upon any man (religious and loyall obedience; <hi>the giving to God the things which are Gods, and unto Caeſar the things which are Caeſars:</hi> the feare of the Lord, and the honour of the King. <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. I alledge the divine curſes againſt bad and diſhoneſt tithing; therfore ſtill rather where a requiſite ſupply and proviſion for the ſufficient mayntenance of ſpirituall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors is wanting.</p>
            <p>It is manifeſt, <hi>Malac.</hi> 3. that as upon the performance of this duty, a marvellous proſperity of the ſeverall fruits of the ground, a gracious opening of the windows of Heaven, and the pouring down plentifull ſhowres of bleſſings are promiſed: So for the neglect and contempt of this notable preſent, confider in the ſame Chapter moſt grievous maledictions threatned.</p>
            <p>Our Elders (Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> expreſſeth) had a happy abundance of all good things, becauſe they were faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the paying to God his tenths, and unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> his Tribute. But ſince that devotion of tithing waxed cold, ſacrilegious perſons have by their covetouſneſſe in that kinde, defrauded themſelves of a double bleſſing; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the promiſes of this life, and of the life to come.</p>
            <p>Other exactions ariſe to puniſh their execrable ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice: what is ſtoln from the Church cannot be preſerved in the cheſt, what is grudged towards the Sanctuary is urged into the treaſury: when men murmure to give
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:27872:40"/>the tenth they are made to forego the totall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dabis impio militi quod non vis dare Sacerdoti,</hi> whiles men deprive the carefull Miniſters, they become a ſpoyle to the cruell ſouldiers. The Lord is always ready and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall to bleſſe; but the wicked perverſneſſe of man op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth wretched impediments to hinder it: for he would have God beſtow all things upon him, and yet hee will offer nothing againe unto this bountifull owner of all things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid faceres, ſi novem partibus ſibi ſumptis tibi decimans reliquiſſet?</hi> What couldeſt thou doe, if hee took all the nine parts to himſelfe, and left the tenth onely unto thee?</p>
            <p>Thus indeed he not ſeldome dealeth when as he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth his former and latter raine, to wither and waſte away thy wiſhed harveſt with a wofull drought: or when hee ſmiteth thy fruits with unſeaſonable ſtormes of hayle: or blaſteth them with extremitie of untimely Froſts.</p>
            <p>And ſo thou grievouſly faileſt of thy covetous and greedy computation, the nine parts being taken away from thee, becauſe thou refuſedſt to pay the tenth which the Lord requited.</p>
            <p>For this is his moſt righteous courſe to turn them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the tenth, which will not offer to him the tenth: to puniſh them with want, which famiſh thoſe which worke.</p>
            <p>Witneſſe either the proper experience of offending perſons, or elſe the events of their poſterities, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the corn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The uſe of the whole premiſes is to admoniſh all ſorts of Chriſtians to practiſe the doctrine of my text: to tithe and conferre towards their Miniſters mayntenance, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rules of holy Writ, within the compaſſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:27872:41"/>of their ſeverall vocations.</p>
            <p>Private perſons muſt apply themſelves unto Chriſtians patience: the properly have no warrantable power to redreſſe and alter publike inconveniences.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe they muſt omit the duty of diligent, and zealous praier unto God, who is able and willing to helpe and ſuccour. They muſt appeare likewiſe cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and forward in any legall courſe, to procure a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt theſe ſacrilegious incroachments and uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations.</p>
            <p>They ought faithfully herein to ayd and further their Miniſters by liberall contribution, and all other juſtifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſiſtances, they (poor men for the moſt part) are leaſt able to undergoe expences: And as the nature of their Calling affordeth commonly ſmall leyſure, ſo concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning temporall affaires they have but litle ſkill and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</p>
            <p>Oh how liberally doe the wiſe children of this world in their generations, ſee their Lawyers in matters apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to their outward eſtates; yea not ſeldome in ſtrifes and contentions, which come from the evill luſts that warre in their members.</p>
            <p>Moreover if a ſickeneſſe ſeizeth on their bodies, they ſpare neither horſes, nor Caroches, nor peeces, no travail nor coſt for a Phyſitian.</p>
            <p>Is it poſſible then that ſuch a multitude of them will ſhew their ſelves ſo baſe and blockiſh, as to grudge and repine almoſt at every penny that they part with, to the heavenly Phyſitians of their ſouls? when as notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the certainty is, that upon the health and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſoule, all the good promiſes, all true welfare of body and eſtate depend.</p>
            <p>Let none then miſerably pinch and ſpare in caſes of this kinde, which indeed be Gods cauſe, and wherein the proſperity of their ſoules, their bodies, their poſterities
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:27872:41"/>be very deeply intereſſed.</p>
            <p>Perſonages of Superior place and ability, as they have the beſt meanes, ſo in no wiſe may they ſlacke behind in cheerefull imployment of them, in every loyall and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full occaſion, to releeve and right our holy and venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mother the Church. They will finde at length, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to bee more noble, pious, nor remunera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>Finally, I beſeech all ſortes, touching the reverend Clergies maintenance, to take into ſerious conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that the God of equity hath in his divine wiſedome, and goodneſſe built his ordinance hereof, upon a faire foundation of equality in all points, and for all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>We cannot ſtray if we ſwerve not from it: wee ſhall not goe wrong, if we regard this rectitude, and erre not through the crookedneſſe of our owne inventions.</p>
            <p>The goods peradventure, of halfe the Chriſtian world conſiſt neither in Paſture nor Tillage, neither in corn, nor pulſe, nor cattle, nor Fruits. A prophane madeneſſe it is to imagine ſuch a manifold number, &amp; populous multitude to be free, &amp; exempted from this manner of ſacred payment.</p>
            <p>As if they acknowledged no ſupreme Head, of whom to hold their riches and ſubſtance in Chief, nor yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, how they had their ſoules under the cure of his Highneſſe Deputies.</p>
            <p>Behold then both prediall and perſonall tithes, muſt yearely be yeelded to ſupply the Lords-Service, with the Miniſtery thereunto, and to ſatisfie all folks with a courſe of indifferency.</p>
            <p>Now although the Clergy ought to endeavour care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, nor to be overcome with evill, but to overcome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill with goodneſſe. And (as Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> chargeth) the Prieſts receiving the tithes of the increaſe, &amp;c. ought not ſluggiſhly to retire from the Altar, <hi>ſed nocte d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>que
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:27872:42"/>ſpiritualibus inſervire,</hi> but night and day to attend upon ſpirituall things; and that under extreme penalties ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>For (to remember us of our duty, and to cut the combe of Church-robbery) <hi>Panormitan</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>Iuſtitutio Beneficiorum fundamentum ſuſcepit finaliter propter cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum divinum, implicantem divinorum miniſterium deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vientium in divinis co loco ubi inſtituuntur,</hi> the finall end of the inſtitution and foundation of Eccleſiaſticall Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices hath beene for the divine worſhip, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery that ſerve therein, in thoſe places, whereas Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livings are ordained.</p>
            <p>Yet dreame not, that the unworthineſſe of the Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Incumbent, will diſcharge the Laytie from theſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; for it this reaſon were currant, it muſt in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner runne upon all other rankes in their kinde, and ſo raiſe a ruinous confuſion upon all degrees.</p>
            <p>Remember therefore the caſe is not onely mans, but Gods eſpecially. Marke how this eternall well-ſpring of mercy, and goodneſſe demandeth backe againe an honeſt returne of this litle portion; and that (without queſtion) not to benefit himſelfe, but to do us the more good, ſaith <hi>Auguſtin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh homines ſtulti, quid mali imper at Deus, ut non mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur audiri?</hi> Oh fooliſh men inſenſible of your owne profits, what hurt doth the Lord command, that you hold him not worthy the hearing?</p>
            <p>That litle which he aſketh, he allotteth to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of his Word and Sacraments unto us. Now ſince theſe actions and agents bee not of mans invention or pleaſure to conſtitute, but of his owne Divine appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and choiſe; why ſhould we then make any doubt or ſcruple, but that his glorious Mejeſtie will likewiſe have meanes and revenues, tithes, and offerings of his owne reſerved to himſelfe, for to ſuſtaine theſe holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:27872:42"/>and ſacred Officers.</p>
            <p>Have a care then every Chriſtian perſon, (according to thy eſtate and calling) to diſcharge thy conſcience in paying thy tithes faithfully. Which Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> termeth neither leſſe nor worſe, our of thy Corne, thy Wine, thy Oyle, thy Fruites, thy Cattel, they Garden, thy Trafficke, thy Hunting, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>Quicunque recognoverit in ſe quod fidelster non dederit decimas emendet quod minus fecit.</q>
            <p>Whoſoever can call to minde that he hath failed in any particular, he is bound in conſcience to amend, and to his power for to make reſtitution.</p>
            <p>Delay not, pay ſpeedily, <hi>Exodus</hi> 22. Grudge not, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murre not, <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> 26. Doe it with gladneſſe: <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticus</hi> 35. Be a cheerfull giver, 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>Pretend no ſacrilegious cuſtomes for thy excuſe: the Popes themſelves allowed this for a Principle, <hi>Revocatur privilegium, ſi ex poſt facto incipit enormiter eſſe nocivum,</hi> An abrogation of their own priviledges when they grew to be very grievous and hurtfull.</p>
            <p>A wrongfull poſſeſſion cannot be warranted by any preſcription of time. What is not right at firſt becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſtill more crooked by continuance. Cuſtome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Divine and Naturall Law is no better then corruption.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſuetudo non praeſtabit ubi per jus expreſſum repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur:</hi> it ought to be of no validity, wheras it affron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth equity and piety.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:27872:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I will not ſay in the words of a learned Civilian, All have robbed, and therfore all are bound to make reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but it behoveth every perſon to put the hallowed things out of his houſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26. to uſurpe nothing to the offence of his conſcience, to the hinderance of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: in no wiſe to diminiſh but rather to augment the Miniſters mayntenance, remembring evermore this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divine precept, <hi>Thou ſhalt muzzle the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the Corn.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Soli Deo, Laus &amp; Gloria. <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27872:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
